<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Startups | Craig Kerstiens]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/categories/startups/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-12T09:23:48-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Craig Kerstiens]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[craig.kerstiens@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What being a PM is really like - Software is easy, People are hard]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2016/01/28/On-being-a-PM-software-is-easy-people-are-hard/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-28T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2016/01/28/On-being-a-PM-software-is-easy-people-are-hard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In recent months I&rsquo;ve had the question nearly once a week about advice/tips for becoming a Product Manager or more commonly referred to as PM. These are generally coming from people that are either currently engineers, or previously were and are in some engineer/customer role such as a sales engineer or solution architect. There&rsquo;s a number of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Inspired-Create-Products-Customers-Love/dp/0981690408?tag=mypred-20">high level</a> pieces talking about PM and it often feels glorious, I mean you get to make product decisions right? You get to call some shots. Well that sometimes may be true, but don&rsquo;t assume it&rsquo;s all rainbows and sparkles.</p>

<p>Especially as a first time PM what your day to day will look like won&rsquo;t be debating strategy all day long. Here&rsquo;s a few of the good and the bad sides of being a PM.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Plenty of grunt work</h3>

<p>While you may get to make a decision or two, the bulk of your time will not be thinking about grandiose visions, instead you&rsquo;ll be doing a lot to gather data. There&rsquo;s a lot of means for gathering data across lots of sources, the more you use the better you&rsquo;ll be. Knowing the ones you steer towards, as well as ones you steer away from is useful so you can balance a bias more fairly. For myself SQL is a go-to, then customer interactions both qualitative and quantitative such as surveys, following what media is saying about your space is important as well. And while user studies are often relegated to design and UX, as a PM you need to make sure it at least happens (<a href="http://www.invisionapp.com/">Invision App</a> is a favorite for lightweight tests).</p>

<p>In a given week I probably spend 10 hrs interacting with customers, looking at data, and sadly that&rsquo;s probably not enough.</p>

<p><em>A few practical examples of this</em></p>

<p>Each morning I send emails to 10-20 users who used the product for the first time, yes this is automated but carving out 30 minutes of my day to actually follow-up with each of them is less automated.</p>

<p>Another example is keeping a health of business dashboard up to date. Personally I use google sheets for this. Within one spreadsheet I have monthly and weekly targets as well as how we’re tracking against them. These are all updated on actual real time data, powered by Heroku’s dataclips with a simple <code>=importCSV(‘http://dataclips.heroku.com/abcdefghij….csv’)</code>. In total my google spreadsheets has 1 high level overview, with about 20 underlying sheets that do all of the computations. In any given month 1 of my key 4-5 goals may be missed, which then spawns digging in deeper to figure out why and what we can do about it.</p>

<h3>Dictating vs. consensus</h3>

<p>From a product decision making perspective you can force alignment by explicitly making every decision, or you can allow decisions to be made as a group voting if needed. Expect to use some balance of both of these among the team, and neither is never perfect. When it comes to outside the team you may still use both, but steer more strongly one way or the other. For example with the executive team it may be more consensus, with marketing it may be dictating your product roadmap which they can help support.</p>

<p>Even within the team there will be times a decision must be made and there will be some people that don&rsquo;t align. It&rsquo;s key that you make the decision clearly and explicitly. Even though some individuals don&rsquo;t like it, they won&rsquo;t fight against it&hellip; unless you make a habit of taking the input, then discarding it and going along your &lsquo;intuition&rsquo;. Even when there&rsquo;s a strong case based on the data it may not be as clear as you think.</p>

<p>In contrast, decision making by consensus most people will feel happier that they provided input into the product. If you take everyone&rsquo;s input expect to end up with a product that feels like 10 people designed it, needless to say incoherent.</p>

<p>As a PM expect to do a lot of listening, a good bit of convincing, and some occasional big decision making.</p>

<h3>The pain you feel inside the building doesn&rsquo;t matter</h3>

<p>You may think you&rsquo;re solving a problem that exists for users, when in reality there was no problem at all. This is just a reminder that you need to keep empathy in mind above so much else.</p>

<p>As an example, once a data team put in place a tool, supposedly for me. I looked at the tool and more or less didn&rsquo;t understand why it was in place. They proceeded to explain that my problem was it took me too long to write SQL, so this tool will help me get the reports I need without SQL. At that point I proceeded to actually list off all the issues I did have, none of which <a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/categories/postgres/">were SQL</a>.</p>

<p>Prescribing a solution without knowing clearly <strong>from customers</strong> what the problem is will leave you in a bad spot. All this means you have to set aside building the tool you want to use, and make sure you know what the <a href="http://headrush.typepad.com/creating_passionate_users/2005/01/keeping_users_e.html">customer wants</a>.</p>

<h3>Marketing is your job</h3>

<p>Not external marketing, though often that work may still fall to you, but rather internal marketing.</p>

<p>It’s important that you internally market the wins for your <em>team</em>. These wins should very much be for the team, and not for your own benefit. The best PMs seem to disappear into the background, this is because you’re more surfacing all the work your team is doing than any of the details you helped coordinate. This is often counter to our natural instinct to tout our own accomplishments. This is only exaggerated in PM role, one where things can still ship if you’re not there, so there can often be a tendency to try to highlight the roles value. Fight that urge to self market.</p>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/f.cl.ly/items/412j330z173E1d432M05/Untitled.png?v=4ceec9d2" style="float:right; width:50%; margin-left:20px;" /></p>

<p>Rest assured though–getting the team focused on solving the right problems, and then surfacing their wins will only help you go faster.</p>

<h3>On leading</h3>

<p><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/f.cl.ly/items/3E2c3k1p1j2g2O1O0b0L/Untitled.png?v=9daf9e58" style="float:right; width:50%; margin-left:20px;margin-bottom:15px;" />
You’ll have to lead at times, follow at others, and all of this will likely be with no reports. Don’t confuse a lack of engineers reporting to you (which they should not, a common team structure can be seen on the right) for not needing to lead the team at times. <em>For those less familiar it’s very rare for a PM to have engineers report to them, though occasionally designers will. It’s typically the cross-reporting structure you’ll find talked about by Andy Grove in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/High-Output-Management-Andrew-Grove/dp/0679762884?tag=mypred-20">High output management</a>.</em> If the team is firing on all cylinders, knows the direction, and executing then step back and let things roll forward. If that’s not the case and leadership around direction or otherwise is needed be prepared to step up.</p>

<p>At the end of the day ensuring the product is advancing is your job, so be prepared to do what you need to whether it’s leading or not to accomplish that.</p>

<h3>It’s not all rainbows, but it is fun</h3>

<p>The range of things you’ll have to focus on can be diverse and complex. In the end if you get a rush out of shipping and launching products, then all the work that goes into it can make it all worthwhile. It’s as much about figuring out what customers want and then getting your team building the right thing. For a first time PM it can be summed up by the notion that software is easy, people are hard.</p>

<p><em>Special thanks to <a href="http://www.twitter.com/lukasfittl">Lukas Fittl</a> and <a href="http://www.twitter.com/iamclovin">Arun Thampi</a> for reviews and feedback on this post.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Marketing definitions for developers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2016/01/17/marketing-definitions-for-developers/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-17T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2016/01/17/marketing-definitions-for-developers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Marketing often feels like a dirty-icky thing to many developers. Well until you feel like you have a great product, but no one using it then you have to get a crash course in all of that. And while I might cover some of the actual basics in the future, just knowing what marketing people actually mean when they’re talking can be a huge jump start. Here&rsquo;s a guide that distills many of the acronyms and terms down to what they actually mean in reality.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><strong>SEO &ndash; Search engine optimization.</strong> There&rsquo;s two sides to this, one where you&rsquo;re attempting to game the system known known as black hat. The other is simply creating good content.</p>

<p>Tip: Now, unlike several years ago social sharing helps impact this.</p>

<p><strong>SEM &ndash; Search engine marketing.</strong> The short of this is adwords, but broadly it&rsquo;s any search engine.</p>

<p>Tip: Be wary here, you can spend a lot of money quickly. Properly managing it takes time and effort otherwise you&rsquo;re wasting money.</p>

<p><strong>Display ads</strong> &ndash; Banner ads on websites. There&rsquo;s a few common form factors in this world, so you&rsquo;ll create a few then reuse them across lots of properties.</p>

<p>Tip: Results may vary here, there are some hidden gems when advertising on various long tail sites.</p>

<p><strong>Retargeting</strong> &ndash; This is where you&rsquo;re serving an ad (most commonly display) to someone that&rsquo;s previously visited your site. The process happens due to you &lsquo;pixeling&rsquo; them, and a cookie being set so the ad server knows they&rsquo;ve seen you.</p>

<p>Tip: Generally good bang for the buck here, but you still need initial visitors to even retarget to.</p>

<p><strong>Funnel</strong> &ndash; The process of someone going from finding you to paying to paying more. Generally a process will look something like: Anonymous visitor by referral, sign ups, low money bucket, big money bucket.</p>

<p><strong>Top of the funnel</strong> &ndash; Hopefully clear from the previous one, top of the funnel would be the max of users you reach out to or get to your site, usually down to getting them to sign up.</p>

<p><strong>Bottom of the funnel</strong> &ndash; This is usually going from time you have a user to customer and then growing that customer via cross-selling and upselling.</p>

<p><strong>Drip marketing</strong> &ndash; This is the process of gradually sending emails/notifications to your customers to get them to engage and learn about the product. Think of it as a welcome email on day 1, an intro on day 3, and on day 5 a different email based on what they&rsquo;ve done so far. Really good drip marketing will create a different email for the user based on what they have or haven&rsquo;t done.</p>

<p><strong>Attribution (last/first/multi)</strong> &ndash; Attribution relates to how you got the user or customer (via web referral). There&rsquo;s a few different ways of looking at this, last touch is the last website they visited before signing up, first touch is the first referral they were sent from, and multi touch (often more complicated to put in place) attributes something to all referrals they&rsquo;ve come from.</p>

<p><strong>AR &ndash; Analyst relations</strong>. Analysts cover particular products or areas in an industry, write reports, and often consult with large enterprises when making buying decisions. Analyst relations or AR is the common term for interacting with them, you can <a href="/2015/07/25/A-guide-to-analyst-relations-for-startups/">learn more here</a></p>

<p><strong>PR &ndash; Public relations</strong>. This is generally the press/media side. It often involves launches, press releases, pitching media etc. You can read more of a <a href="/2015/07/21/An-intro-PR-guide-for-startups/">guide on it here</a></p>

<p><strong>Briefing</strong> &ndash; This is normally with an analyst or press, and is typically a quick 30 minute call occasionally a demo of an upcoming launch.Usually</p>

<p><strong>Inquiry</strong> &ndash; This refers more to the analyst side. Where a briefing is often more one sided for you to pitch/update them on what you’ve been doing, an inquiry is more a back and forth where you can ask what they’re seeing in the market and for input on direction.</p>

<p><strong>Campaign</strong> &ndash; A collection of activities that go on around a certain thing focused on specific keywords or theme. This can be as little as a search engine marketing campaign which is the most common, or much larger and coordinated with billboards, webinars, etc.</p>

<p><strong>Lead Gen</strong> &ndash; The sales funnel usually goes from just getting an email, to talking to them, to getting them to try a demo or run a POC, to eventually buying. Lead gen is the activity of just getting that initial contact so you can then further engage with them. In practice this can often involve giving something away, like a t-shirt in exchange for an email.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>While this doesn&rsquo;t cover every marketing activity under the sun, hopefully it&rsquo;s a good primer on things you may have heard but been confused by. If there&rsquo;s important ones I&rsquo;ve missed please feel free to let me know <a href="http://www.twitter.com/craigkerstiens">@craigkerstiens</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Seeding a sharing-economy or platform company]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2015/10/02/seeding-a-sharing-economy-or-platform-company/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2015/10/02/seeding-a-sharing-economy-or-platform-company</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>These days if you&rsquo;re creating a company you likely hope to accomplish more with less people, two ways of doing this fall to: The sharing economy and creating a platform. It&rsquo;s easy to see the case for this when you have such <a href="http://graphics.wsj.com/billion-dollar-club/">unicorns</a> like AirBnB or Uber. The opportunity for each of those to compete against hotel chains or taxi services which each need to manage their own inventory is incredibly exciting and revolutionary. In a similar fashion platforms can offer much the same, Heroku&rsquo;s platform and marketplace made it easier than ever for developers to click a button and get everything they needed years ago. It&rsquo;s not just their code, it&rsquo;s everything from <a href="https://www.heroku.com/postgres">Postgres</a> to Mongo to <a href="https://elements.heroku.com/addons#logging">Logging</a>. Or take the app store as example. Smart phones weren&rsquo;t a new thing when the iPhone came out, but it was only the saviest of users that had apps installed on their windows smartphone or blackberry. The app store made the iPhone different than any other phone by allowing others to build and improve it, turning the iPhone not into a phone but a platform.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Platforms and the sharing economy both let you get further than having to take on the costs of offering the equivilent all on your own. And while a great idea to venture into one of these two areas, starting them isn&rsquo;t as trivial as simply deciding to. For both of these you have issues with having a two sided market, first you have to convince the providers to come along, then the customers or vice versa. As a result of this two sided market issue the easiest way to actually start is by bootstrapping it yourself – or faking it til you make it.</p>

<p>What are some good examples of faking this? I&rsquo;m sure you can probably find some good stories going back about AirBnB or Uber, but let&rsquo;s assume times were different then. Let&rsquo;s take a look at a very recent example: <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2015/08/26/lugg-an-app-for-on-demand-short-distance-moves-raises-3-8-million/">Lugg</a> which just launched in the latest batch of YC. Lugg is Uber for moving essentially, allowing you to on-demand request furniture moved from one place to another. Early on Lugg built their app, then waited for requests to come in, then the founders got in a truck and moved the furniture themselves. As a customer the founders are likely providing a great experience, without ever having to tip their hat at the ways their hacking the impression of being a large well oiled machine.</p>

<p>But what about a platform? Slack continues to grow like wildfire as the new medium for communication. These days there&rsquo;s endless integrations for slack, and I expect they&rsquo;ll continue to expand what a platform for communication looks like. But a year ago they were quite a ways from having people show up at their door to add an integration. Sure there were people using them, but to expect github/trello/asana to immediately build an integration for every new flavor of the week tool would be crazy. Yet, without these integrations slack wouldn&rsquo;t be nearly as useful as it is today–and probably wouldn&rsquo;t have seen the growth it&rsquo;s seen. In the early days of a platform the easiest way to get these integrations and partners in place is to show up and build the work yourself. Slack carried the weight early of building these integrations, much as Heroku add-ons showed up at partners offices and help write the code to get them as a provider in the marketplace. And while both Slack and Heroku are larger companies now, it still holds true for smaller ones starting today. <a href="https://www.blockspring.com/">Blockspring</a>, a company which aims to make web services available through spreadsheets, had to do very much the same thing building their initial integrations themselves. Now with their rapidly growing user base and already large collection of APIs they may be able to shift the model, but early on that wasn&rsquo;t so much an option.</p>

<p>If you want to build a platform, start by creating the impression of one while still carrying the load yourself. Yes, move to a true platform as soon as you can, but don&rsquo;t wait for others to show up before you go that route.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A guide to analyst relations for startups]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2015/07/25/A-guide-to-analyst-relations-for-startups/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2015/07/25/A-guide-to-analyst-relations-for-startups</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When it comes to go to market and marketing there&rsquo;s lots of pieces in a toolchest that all work together. One that comes a bit later, but if used properly (much like a <a href="/2015/07/21/An-intro-PR-guide-for-startups/">PR agency</a>) can be valuable is industry analysts. And while working with a PR agency can quickly start to become clear. How to work with analysts so it is productive on both sides can take a bit longer to figure out, or at least it did for me. Even before you do start working with them there&rsquo;s the question of if or when should you. Here&rsquo;s hoping this primer makes it a bit faster and easier for others.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>What is an analyst</h3>

<p><em>Apologies to all analysts, but of all parts of this post I might butcher this one</em></p>

<p>Analysts talk to a lot of companies, both the ones making products as well as the ones purchasing them. I&rsquo;m not actually sure what the spread is I&rsquo;d guess 80-20. A large output of this and other activities is  creating various reports and rankings. Gartner&rsquo;s Magic Quadrant is probably the most well known industry ranking. Much of what they create isn&rsquo;t freely available for consumption so you likely don&rsquo;t see the sheer volume of insights they put out.</p>

<h3>Why would you engage with an analyst</h3>

<p>So what do they do for you? There’s really two major buckets:</p>

<p><strong>Help with sales/marketing</strong> &ndash; Given they&rsquo;re informing and influencing buying decisions of businesses they can be one more person on your side. If a launch in Techcrunch makes business foo aware of product bar, then an analyst report or ranking can help sway a decision on whether to try bar vs. baz.</p>

<p><strong>Consulting</strong> &ndash; The other major opportunity is for the analyst to give some form of guidance. In a larger company when you already have an established product they should absolutely be part of your launch process (more on that in a future post). They&rsquo;re actively following your market and space, hopefully just as you are to some extent. They can offer an outside perspective and help with broad areas of focus and messaging.</p>

<p><em>More</em> &ndash; In reality it’s as clean cut as above. They may be able to introduce you to good candidates for hiring. They may be able to introduce you to a large company interested in acquiring some capability which you have. They may be able to connect you with investors. All of these things can and do happen, but the above buckets typically are the primary drivers.</p>

<h3>When?</h3>

<p>First, engaging with analysts should always come after you have some confidence in the product, after you&rsquo;ve started some marketing drumbeat, and after sales. In short don&rsquo;t be in a huge rush here, you&rsquo;ll get there, but don&rsquo;t be in too big of a rush. As you start to get some attention and momentum it&rsquo;s just as likely they&rsquo;ll engage with you first as you reaching out. Also, marketing != sales, more on that in a future post.</p>

<p>But, let&rsquo;s assume you&rsquo;ve got a product <strong>which targets business</strong> (<em>Analysts aren&rsquo;t just for tech companies, though you’ll see the benefit here sooner if you’re say a database company than a HR product</em>). Let’s also assume you&rsquo;ve got some sales and have some <a href="/2015/07/21/An-intro-PR-guide-for-startups/">good launches under your belt</a>. As it starts to come up in sales calls if you&rsquo;re in any industry reports or rankings that may be an indicator, if you&rsquo;re hearing about other competitors having more validation in such reports. As a general rule of thumb once you&rsquo;ve got inhouse PR they should be able to help guide and steer to the right time.</p>

<h3>So how do you engage with an analyst</h3>

<p>If you&rsquo;re engaging in some form of report or article, that should start to be pretty self explanatory. They&rsquo;ll send you a questionnaire, you fill it out. You go back and forth a little bit.</p>

<p>However, the majority of my interactions aren&rsquo;t on those articles and reports, for ever one time I fill out lots of questions to help some report or ranking I have 20 calls with an analyst.</p>

<p>There are two primary calls you can have, an inquiry and a briefing.</p>

<h4>Inquiries</h4>

<p>Inquiry is just a fancy word for consulting call. An inquiry you will always be paying for.</p>

<p><em>A small detour here. The regularity and consistency in which you engage with an analyst makes a difference. They&rsquo;re also people at the end of the day, so while firms have certain styles it&rsquo;s even further multiplied by being very people driven. In your interactions you&rsquo;ll have a different rapport with different people, it&rsquo;s at a minimum important to be aware of this.</em></p>

<p>So back to an inquiry. Within an inquiry your goal is to pull back the curtain and give some backstage insights into what you&rsquo;re doing and where you&rsquo;re headed. This is typically under NDA and trust the NDA of an analyst. It&rsquo;s worthwhile to be as candid as you can here, yes it feels weird, but you&rsquo;ll get the most value. They&rsquo;re not like that of a reporter looking for a scoop (not that you can&rsquo;t trust reporters, just know if you say it, it&rsquo;s on record). You don&rsquo;t have to relish the entire call to one area, but areas of coverage are often:</p>

<ul>
<li>Upcoming products and major releases you’re working on</li>
<li>Broader strategy and roadmap</li>
<li>Get input on what they&rsquo;re seeing and hearing from customers</li>
</ul>


<h4>Briefings</h4>

<p>The other type of call we have is a briefing. This is a little similar to that of a press briefing. You&rsquo;ll get on the call, and walk through some upcoming launch or just give an update on your company and progress. The latter is more common if they&rsquo;re unfamiliar with you or your product.</p>

<p>Analyst briefings are good to do earlier than your press briefings, compared to press they&rsquo;re like a bike with training wheels. It&rsquo;s best if you still maintain your balance–the ride will be smoother, but there&rsquo;s a little less risk of completely toppling over. One key difference is you often have a powerpoint deck you get to walk through during an analyst briefing. I&rsquo;ve found this is helpful for pacing and key messages, I used to be skeptical, but now very much feel it&rsquo;s always worth doing.</p>

<p><em>Pro-tip: You can create a deck and use it for press too, no they won&rsquo;t want to get on a gotomeeting, but you can send it over so they have more content later. BUT, more importantly you can also walk through it on your own screen if it helps with pacing.</em></p>

<p>Within a briefing you&rsquo;ll have some ability to ask them questions at points. Does this resonate? Are you hearing similar? What are you seeing in the market? Don&rsquo;t turn it into an inquiry, but knowing the parts that hit home for them allow you to refine your pitch for the next call.</p>

<h4>Engaging &ndash; the tactical parts</h4>

<p>&ldquo;Analysts are pretty much paid to talk and write&rdquo; &ndash; <a href="http://www.twitter.com/cote">@cote</a>. So expect that often when you occupy their time there&rsquo;s a price to it. In terms of finding them it should be pretty easy, to know the list of ones in your space, you may see them quoted or reference in various media outlets. You may just naturally crop up in a report.</p>

<p>If you create a regular relationship with them you&rsquo;ll have some contract of hours over the course of a quarter or year. At an early stage company this is often owned and manage by whomever runs your PR from an internal perspective.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>If you&rsquo;re about to engage with analysts for the first time or haven’t figured out how to get the most out of your interactions I hope the broad overview is helpful. If there&rsquo;s some glaring parts you feel I&rsquo;ve missed let me know <a href="http://www.twitter.com/craigkerstiens">@craigkerstiens</a>. And for further reading/watching I’d encourage checking out the great talk from <a href="http://www.twitter.com/cote">@cote</a> in the <a href="http://www.heavybit.com/library/video/2014-01-21-michael-cote">Heavybit library</a>.</p>

<p>As far as take-aways and a recap:</p>

<ol>
<li>Don&rsquo;t be too eager to jump in with analysts. They can absolutely provide value, but you have to put some time in before it really starts to pay off. It&rsquo;s not an overnight change and takes building a rapport with them.</li>
<li>At the same time, analysts can be useful in many B2B areas not just tech ones.</li>
<li>When in an inquiry be open and as transparent as possible.</li>
<li>Powerpoint/Keynote/Google presentations are useful in briefings, even if it&rsquo;s just for you to follow along.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A guide to PR for startups]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2015/07/21/An-intro-PR-guide-for-startups/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2015/07/21/An-intro-PR-guide-for-startups</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You&rsquo;ve built your product and you&rsquo;re now ready for your first major launch. Or you&rsquo;ve been through a launch or two, but are looking to scale the process as you&rsquo;re doing more launches and announcements. You really have two options: do it <a href="http://jasonlbaptiste.com/featured-articles/how-i-pitched-techcrunch-and-13-ways-to-get-press-when-you-launch-your-startup/">all on your own</a>, or work with a PR agency. One frequent crossroad is that you&rsquo;re not at the point of a full time PR person, but unsure what a PR agency can offer you; and, further what&rsquo;s the best way to work with them so you&rsquo;re getting the maximum value.</p>

<p>As I&rsquo;ve talked to more startups lately, it&rsquo;s become clear that effectively working with PR teams and the media is mostly learned by doing. Because there&rsquo;s not much guidance out there, here&rsquo;s an attempt at some basic guidelines.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>On PR</h3>

<p>First there&rsquo;s two types here and they&rsquo;re not mutually exclusive. In-house PR is a full time person or team that works within your company, here you&rsquo;ll often have a pretty different experience. From my experience, in-house PR people tend to understand a company message and vision because they are living and breathing your company values every day.</p>

<p>The other alternative is hiring a PR agency. An agency will have several (sometimes hundreds!) of clients. The relationship that you’ll have with an agency is much different than in-house. You&rsquo;ll use them just like you would a consultant or contractor. Most startups end up with the agency approach first, because of the perception of “more people working for a cheaper cost than hiring in-house.” However, it&rsquo;s of note an agency doesn&rsquo;t alleviate you of doing work, nor should you want them to handle all parts of it.</p>

<h4>Messaging</h4>

<p>An agency may offer to help with messaging, but take this somewhat lightly. I don&rsquo;t doubt that some are very good at it, but in most cases I&rsquo;ve found they don&rsquo;t have the same amount of customer interaction as you as a founder or early employee would. Further, your vision of impact to the market and direction may be more distant than theirs. You should expect to own your messaging, just like you own your product.</p>

<p>Where they can heavily help is providing a lot of structured frameworks for helping you get to your messaging. Some pretty basic templates of standard questions for customers and partners can go along way in helping you actually uncover what they feel your value is.</p>

<p><em>On your key messaging/value prop, there&rsquo;s two pieces I&rsquo;ll drop in here. While I&rsquo;d love to write another long post on it, I wonder when I&rsquo;ll actually get it out. So the first is pitch the problem you&rsquo;re trying to solve–<a href="http://500hats.typepad.com/500blogs/2009/08/your-solution-is-not-my-problem.html">Dave McClure</a> talks about this as well as anyone. The second is don&rsquo;t pitch features, pitch the use cases and solutions. Pitch what&rsquo;s possible</em></p>

<h4>Pitching</h4>

<p>This is the number one area I&rsquo;ve found that having PR makes a huge difference. In the world of reporting, different reporters have different beats (areas of coverage), styles, outreach preferences, and most importantly, different relationships with companies and people. Knowing <em>all</em> of this and how to pitch a story to them is key. Yes you can spend hours researching and creating a perfect story just for them, and do that again, and again and hopefully land some coverage. But I&rsquo;d argue a bit: that&rsquo;s not the best use of your time.</p>

<p>With a good PR person or agency you&rsquo;ll be able to strike a mix of:</p>

<ul>
<li>Here&rsquo;s the outlets I want to be in and why (have a good reason for why).</li>
<li>Understanding the audience and readership.</li>
<li>What outlets you feel like your key customers are reading, and validate this with the agency.</li>
</ul>


<p>From there, if you&rsquo;ve found a good agency they already have relationships with your key journalists / publications. So if you have a compelling product, you just need to give them the right messaging of the particular launch or news.</p>

<h4>What else to expect from your agency</h4>

<p>A surprise for some is how the whole process works. The agency is going to be there on the phone with you. You&rsquo;re not going to hang out over beers while pitching being chummy. The reporter is listening to multiple other pitches, it&rsquo;s likely they had one right before you and right after. The agency is there listening, helping keep time and track of conversation for reporter fact-checking after the interview.</p>

<p>Hopefully they&rsquo;re also keeping notes. They should be able to provide you with some high level notes of what message resonated with each reporter and what didn&rsquo;t, what you covered, and what they asked. This is especially useful for future interactions.</p>

<p>Similarly you should get a briefing 1 pager ahead of time. You should be able to skim this, you don&rsquo;t have to memorize. But it&rsquo;ll include key things about recent articles written by the reporter, their beat, topics to dive into and ones to stay away from. If you can connect the dots, those notes from an initial call start to feed into the 1 pagers for future calls.</p>

<h3>Onto the briefing</h3>

<p>Of course it&rsquo;s important to land the briefing in the first place, but just as important is getting it right. Coming into it, the reporter will have already gotten the high level pitch&hellip; It&rsquo;s why they took the call. You&rsquo;ll get a mixed bag of those that are open to teeing up the opportunity to those that want to get right to the news. Roll with what they prefer, but also don&rsquo;t be afraid of trying to hit some of your key points.</p>

<h4>Have your key messages ready</h4>

<p>Sound bites help hugely here. Analogies, customer references, whatever you want to hit. Have it ready. Also if you&rsquo;ve got a great sound bite that helps tell the story, it can make the reporter&rsquo;s job easier. Just don&rsquo;t swing too far into happy go lucky marketing land. It’s important to remember that you’re talking to a person. Have a conversation &ndash; don’t talk at them.</p>

<h4>Go slow</h4>

<p>It may seem obvious when you think about it, but as you&rsquo;re talking the reporter is writing. Or at least you hope they are. Some do it by hand and type up notes late, some type right then and there. When you hear a pause it doesn&rsquo;t always mean to keep going and it seldom means hurry up. Become extra comfortable with pauses. Check in if you&rsquo;re going to fast, if they&rsquo;re following, if they have any questions. I&rsquo;ve had people bring me in a beer before because I&rsquo;d had multiple cups of coffee through a few pitches, and they were trying to slow me down a bit. Know your pace, and then slow it down.</p>

<h4>Questions</h4>

<p>It&rsquo;s okay if they don&rsquo;t have a lot of questions, they may not. They may have none at all. Yes, pause, and give them a chance, or even ask if they have any. But don&rsquo;t stress too much if they have no questions.</p>

<p>On the flip side of that &ndash; you’re PR person should have prepared a list of questions for you beforehand that the reporter could possibly throw your way. Be sure you’ve thought through and practiced all the Q&amp;A scenarios before the interview so you aren’t caught off-guard when you’re in front of the reporter.</p>

<h3>In conclusion</h3>

<p>If it&rsquo;s your first go around, don&rsquo;t stress too much. Have the headlines you want in your mind and key messages, or better yet write them out. <em>Personally I write key things on a whiteboard nice and large before I&rsquo;m on the call</em>. Finally once you&rsquo;re all done, enjoy reading the coverage. <strong>But you&rsquo;re not all done</strong> after you get some coverage look back, run a retrospective just like you would for a software project. What worked well, why did or didn&rsquo;t something work. What can you improve next time.</p>

<p>*Full disclosure, this is based across interactions with a small sample size of different PR agencies and individuals. Mileage may differ heavily from PR firm to PR firm, but hopefully the above provides at least some roadmap for more clarity vs. flying blind. As always if you&rsquo;ve got feedback/questions, feel free to let me know <a href="http://www.twitter.com/craigkerstiens">@craigkerstiens</a></p>

<p><em>Finally a special thanks to <a href="http://www.twitter.com/pavtalk">Paul Katsen</a> for much of the inspiration on creating this post and to he and <a href="http://www.twitter.com">Katie Boysen</a> for review</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
