<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Craig Kerstiens]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-07T12:27:24-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Craig Kerstiens]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[craig.kerstiens@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Postgres Datatypes – The ones you're not using.]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/05/08/Postgres-datatypes-the-ones-youre-not-using/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/05/08/Postgres-datatypes-the-ones-youre-not-using</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://cl.ly/image/0V3d2A0w2V0N/Naws__Its_all_just_1_s_and_0_s.png" style="float:right;" />Postgres has a variety of datatypes, in fact quite a few more than most other databases. Most commonly applications take advantage of the standard ones – integers, text, numeric, etc. Almost every application needs these basic types, the rarer ones may be needed less frequently. And while not needed on every application when you do need them they can be an extremely handy. So without further adieu let&rsquo;s look at some of these rarer but awesome types.</p>

<h3>hstore</h3>

<p>Yes, I&rsquo;ve talked about <a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/07/03/hstore-vs-json/">this one before</a>, yet still not enough people are using it. Of this list of datatypes this is one that could also have benefit for most if not all applications. <!--more-->Hstore is a key-value store directly within Postgres. This means you can easily add new keys and values <em>(optionally)</em>, without haveing to run a migration to setup new columns. Further you can still get great performance by using Gin and GiST indexes with them, which automatically index all keys and values for hstore.</p>

<h3>Range types</h3>

<p>If there is ever a time where you have two columns in your database with one being a from, another being a to, you probably want to be using <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.2/static/rangetypes.html">range types</a>. Range types are just that a set of ranges. A super common use of them is when doing anything with calendaring. The place where they really become useful is in their ability to apply constraints on those ranges. This means you can make sure you don&rsquo;t have overlapping time issues, and don&rsquo;t have to rebuild heavy application logic to accomplish it.</p>

<h3>Timestamp with Timezone</h3>

<p>Timestamps are annoying, plain and simple. If you&rsquo;ve re-invented handling different timezones within your application you&rsquo;ve wasted plenty of time and likely done it wrong. If you&rsquo;re using plain timestamps within your application further there&rsquo;s a good chance they dont even mean what you think they mean. Timestamps with timezone or timestamptz automatically includes the timezone with the timestamp. This makes it easy to convert between timezones, know exactly what you&rsquo;re dealing with, and will in short save you a ton of time. There&rsquo;s seldom a case you shouldn&rsquo;t be using these.</p>

<h3>UUID</h3>

<p>Integers are primary keys aren&rsquo;t great. Sure if you&rsquo;re running a small blog they work fine, but if you&rsquo;re application has to scale to a large size integers can create problems. First you can run out of them, second it can make other details such as sharding a little more annoying. At the same time they are super readable. However, using the actual UUID datatype and extension to automatically generate them can be incredibly handy if you have to scale an application.</p>

<h3>Binary JSON</h3>

<p>This isn&rsquo;t available yet, but will be in Postgres 9.4. Binary JSON is of course JSON directly within your database, but also lets you add Gin indexes directly onto JSON. This means a much simpler setup in not only inserting JSON, but having fast reads. If you want to learn a bit more about this, <a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/training/index.html">sign up</a> to <a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/training/index.html">get notified</a> of training regarding the upcoming PostgreSQL 9.4 release.</p>

<h3>Money</h3>

<p>Please don&rsquo;t use this&hellip; The money datatype assumes a single currency type, and generally brings with it more caveats than simply using a numeric type.</p>

<h3>In conclusion</h3>

<p>What&rsquo;d I miss? What are you&rsquo;re favorite types? Let me know <a href="http://www.twitter.com/craigkerstiens">@craigkerstiens</a>, or sign-up below to updates on Postgres content and first access to training.</p>

<!-- Begin MailChimp Signup Form -->


<p><link href="//cdn-images.mailchimp.com/embedcode/classic-081711.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"></p>



<div id="mc_embed_signup">
<form action="http://craigkerstiens.us5.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc&amp;id=dacc2c6d9a" method="post" id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <h2>Sign up to get weekly advice and content on Postgres</h2>
<div class="indicates-required"><span class="asterisk">*</span> indicates required</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
    <label for="mce-EMAIL">Email Address  <span class="asterisk">*</span>
</label>
    <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="required email" id="mce-EMAIL">
</div>
    <div id="mce-responses" class="clear">
        <div class="response" id="mce-error-response" style="display:none"></div>
        <div class="response" id="mce-success-response" style="display:none"></div>
    </div>    <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
    <div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;"><input type="text" name="b_0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc_dacc2c6d9a" tabindex="-1" value=""></div>
    <div class="clear"><input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button"></div>
</form>
</div>


<script type="text/javascript">
var fnames = new Array();var ftypes = new Array();fnames[0]='EMAIL';ftypes[0]='email';
try {
    var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    jqueryLoaded=true;
} catch(err) {
    var jqueryLoaded=false;
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
if (!jqueryLoaded) {
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = '//ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.4.4/jquery.min.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    if (script.readyState && script.onload!==null){
        script.onreadystatechange= function () {
              if (this.readyState == 'complete') mce_preload_check();
        }    
    }
}

var err_style = '';
try{
    err_style = mc_custom_error_style;
} catch(e){
    err_style = '#mc_embed_signup input.mce_inline_error{border-color:#6B0505;} #mc_embed_signup div.mce_inline_error{margin: 0 0 1em 0; padding: 5px 10px; background-color:#6B0505; font-weight: bold; z-index: 1; color:#fff;}';
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
var style= document.createElement('style');
style.type= 'text/css';
if (style.styleSheet) {
  style.styleSheet.cssText = err_style;
} else {
  style.appendChild(document.createTextNode(err_style));
}
head.appendChild(style);
setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);

var mce_preload_checks = 0;
function mce_preload_check(){
    if (mce_preload_checks>40) return;
    mce_preload_checks++;
    try {
        var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = 'http://downloads.mailchimp.com/js/jquery.form-n-validate.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    try {
        var validatorLoaded=jQuery("#fake-form").validate({});
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    mce_init_form();
}
function mce_init_form(){
    jQuery(document).ready( function($) {
      var options = { errorClass: 'mce_inline_error', errorElement: 'div', onkeyup: function(){}, onfocusout:function(){}, onblur:function(){}  };
      var mce_validator = $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").validate(options);
      $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").unbind('submit');//remove the validator so we can get into beforeSubmit on the ajaxform, which then calls the validator
      options = { url: 'http://craigkerstiens.us5.list-manage.com/subscribe/post-json?u=0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc&id=dacc2c6d9a&c=?', type: 'GET', dataType: 'json', contentType: "application/json; charset=utf-8",
                    beforeSubmit: function(){
                        $('#mce_tmp_error_msg').remove();
                        $('.datefield','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var txt = 'filled';
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        var bday = false;
                                        if (fields.length == 2){
                                            bday = true;
                                            fields[2] = {'value':1970};//trick birthdays into having years
                                        }
                                        if ( fields[0].value=='MM' && fields[1].value=='DD' && (fields[2].value=='YYYY' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else if ( fields[0].value=='' && fields[1].value=='' && (fields[2].value=='' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else {
                                            if (/\[day\]/.test(fields[0].name)){
                                                this.value = fields[1].value+'/'+fields[0].value+'/'+fields[2].value;                                           
                                            } else {
                                                this.value = fields[0].value+'/'+fields[1].value+'/'+fields[2].value;
                                            }
                                        }
                                    });
                            });
                        $('.phonefield-us','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        if ( fields[0].value.length != 3 || fields[1].value.length!=3 || fields[2].value.length!=4 ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else {
                                            this.value = 'filled';
                                        }
                                    });
                            });
                        return mce_validator.form();
                    }, 
                    success: mce_success_cb
                };
      $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').ajaxForm(options);
      
      
    });
}
function mce_success_cb(resp){
    $('#mce-success-response').hide();
    $('#mce-error-response').hide();
    if (resp.result=="success"){
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(resp.msg);
        $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').each(function(){
            this.reset();
        });
    } else {
        var index = -1;
        var msg;
        try {
            var parts = resp.msg.split(' - ',2);
            if (parts[1]==undefined){
                msg = resp.msg;
            } else {
                i = parseInt(parts[0]);
                if (i.toString() == parts[0]){
                    index = parts[0];
                    msg = parts[1];
                } else {
                    index = -1;
                    msg = resp.msg;
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            index = -1;
            msg = resp.msg;
        }
        try{
            if (index== -1){
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);            
            } else {
                err_id = 'mce_tmp_error_msg';
                html = '<div id="'+err_id+'" style="'+err_style+'"> '+msg+'</div>';
                
                var input_id = '#mc_embed_signup';
                var f = $(input_id);
                if (ftypes[index]=='address'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-addr1';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else if (ftypes[index]=='date'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-month';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else {
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index];
                    f = $().parent(input_id).get(0);
                }
                if (f){
                    $(f).append(html);
                    $(input_id).focus();
                } else {
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
        }
    }
}

</script>


<!--End mc_embed_signup-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What you need to know about April 7 and your security on the web.]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/04/08/What-you-need-to-know-about-april-7-and-the-web/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/04/08/What-you-need-to-know-about-april-7-and-the-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://heartbleed.com/heartbleed.png" style="float:right;margin-left:20px;height:300px;"/>
On April 7 a vulnerability, nicknamed heartbleed, was discovered in a programming library that helps power somewhere over half of the internet. In the most basic sense this library allowed intentional external parties to acquire data that was thought to be safe and secure from whomever was running a vulnerable website. There was little to know one that was except from this due to their security practices, major examples of sites that were affected include:</p>

<ul>
<li>Yahoo</li>
<li>Amazon.com</li>
<li>Netflix</li>
<li>Various banks</li>
<li>Many more</li>
</ul>


<p>If you&rsquo;re interested in more technical details you can <a href="http://www.heartbleed.com">follow along</a> or on the <a href="https://blog.heroku.com/archives/2014/4/8/openssl_heartbleed_security_update">Heroku blog</a>.</p>

<p>The short of it is you, yes you as in everyone, should rotate your passwords once all websites are safe. For further details please continue reading.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>What does the vulnerability mean</h3>

<p><img src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/Bks0vXLIUAAaexR.jpg" style="float:right;margin-left:10px;"/> In this case it allowed an external party to acquire a moderate amount of data from some computer running your website. Extremely clear examples (such as shown on the right) highlight an example of random third parties easily acquiring most recently logged in Yahoo mail usernames and passwords.</p>

<h3>The first step</h3>

<p>The first step in resolving this is actually not a step required by you at all, unless you&rsquo;re running a production website online. The first step requires the developers running the site to update their site so they are no longer vulnerable. This as available to happen as early as April 7, and many major sites were fully updated and again safe as of April 8.</p>

<h3>Still area for concern</h3>

<p>With security vulnerabilities there are two key things to consider. First is the vulnerability itself, second is whether its therotical or can be simply acted upon. Yes, there&rsquo;s a range here. One of the most unfortunate pieces from talking to those that know about security is this was extremely trivial to act upon.</p>

<p><em>This is made even worse in that this vulnerability has existed for 2 years without many knowing about it, meaning people have had an ability to snoop and collect parts of your data for two years</em></p>

<h3>What to do?</h3>

<p>First things first, be extremely cautious with any major website you connect with anything important. Any account that you have a password and you care about the account you should cease logging into it <strong>until you know its safe</strong>. As of the morning of April 8 here is a <a href="https://gist.github.com/dberkholz/10169691">list of sites that were safe and ones that were vulnerable</a>. You can check any site today <a href="http://filippo.io/Heartbleed/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Once it&rsquo;s clear that a site you know is now updated and safe either via that list of the latter tool you should change your password. For the time that this has existed and ease of comprimising its safe to assume all of your internet passwords and data within those accounts could have been comprimised. This means any website you have logged into within the last two years you should change the password for. Changing your passwords limits anyone being able to access that again.</p>

<p><em>I am not a security expert or analyst, but have heavily interacted with many that are in dealing with this incident. This advice is high level intended at non technical experts, if you have any questions or feedback please let me know on twitter <a href="http://www.twitter.com/craigkerstiens">@craigkerstiens</a></em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some non-traditional marketing tips]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/03/31/some-short-untypical-marketing-tips/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/03/31/some-short-untypical-marketing-tips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Marketing is generally unexciting to a ton of engineers, until it brings eyeballs which bring feedback and dollars. Marketing doesn&rsquo;t have to always be cheesy campaigns or ads, it can often just be surfacing the things your customers actually do want to care about. My favorite type of marketing is when a service sells me on something at the exact time I want it. Here&rsquo;s a few short tips on some non-traditional marketing that won&rsquo;t seem sleezy but still can work quite well.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Email subscriptions to your blog</h3>

<p>RSS is pretty dead, google went and killed it with google reader. Sure there&rsquo;s some decent replacements if you&rsquo;re really tied to it. In particular <a href="http://newsblur.com/">newsblur</a> by <a href="http://www.twitter.com/samuelclay">@samuelclay</a> is a great reader. But now days content emerges on twitter, fb, and ranking services, then later is discovered via search. Both of these work pretty well, but twitter is ephemeral for so many. Email still converts incredibly well, if people are abandoning rss but still care about your content give them the ability for it to be put right in front of their face via email.</p>

<h3>Market in transactional emails</h3>

<p>Have emails that include receipts? Account confirmations? General notices? No not a monthly newsletter! Transactional emails are obviously valuable to your users. Why not include a small call out to your latest announcement? Have a central hook that your emails can check from and simply include a small call to action within there.</p>

<p><em>Credit to <a href="http://www.twitter.com/stevenbristol">@stevenbristol</a> on <a href="http://strongbusinessespodcast.com/16571/149964-episode-17-security-authy-and-disney">strong business podcast</a> for this one</em></p>

<h3>Retarget to your existing users</h3>

<p>In a similar vein of notifying your existing customers in transactional emails about news, you should be doing this all over the web. Retargeting is great to convert people once you&rsquo;ve already got them on a landing page, but its also incredibly useful to get existing users to <a href="http://insideintercom.io/talk-product-strategy-saying/">use a specific feature</a>. If you track if they&rsquo;ve never used a feature retargeting is a great way to make them aware of it, and once they&rsquo;ve used it just count it as a conversion.</p>

<p><em>My favorite retargeting provider <a href="http://www.perfectaudience.com/">perfect audience</a> makes this quite convenient as they allow a bit more control than most retargeting services</em></p>

<h3>In conclusion</h3>

<p>Marketing doesn&rsquo;t have to be throwing your product and messaging in someones face, but you should make your users aware of it. The more engaged they are they more they&rsquo;ll stick around and be happy about using you&rsquo;re product, assuming you&rsquo;ve built a good one. What are some of your favorite tips?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A year's look at Postgres]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/03/26/a-year-of-postgres/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/03/26/a-year-of-postgres</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple years back I started more regularly blogging, though I&rsquo;ve done this off and on before, this time I kept some regularity. A common theme started to emerge with some content on Postgres about once a month because most of what was out there was much more reference oriented. A bit after that I connected with <a href="http://www.twitter.com/peterc">petercooper</a>, who runs quite a few weekly email newsletters. As someone thats been interested helping give others a good reason to create content the obvious idea of <a href="http://www.postgresweekly.com">Postgres Weekly</a> emerged.</p>

<p>Since then we&rsquo;ve now had the newsletter running for over a year, helped surface quite a bit of content, and grown to over 5,000 subscribers. First if you&rsquo;re not subscribed, then go <a href="http://www.postgresweekly.com">subscribe now</a>.</p>

<p>And if you need some inspiration or just want to reminisce with me&hellip; here&rsquo;s a look back at a few highlights over the past year:</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>The inagural issue</h3>

<h4><a href="http://postgres-bits.herokuapp.com/?utm_source=craigkerstiens&amp;utm_medium=blog">Postgres: The Bits You Haven&rsquo;t Found</a></h4>

<p>A slide-deck from a presentation at Heroku&rsquo;s Waza conference that highlights many of the more unknown and rare features within Postgres, including &lsquo;WITH&rsquo;, arrays, pub/sub, and hstore.</p>

<h4><a href="http://blog.aggregateknowledge.com/2013/02/04/open-source-release-postgresql-hll/?utm_source=craigkerstiens&amp;utm_medium=blog">Open Source Release:postgresql-hll</a></h4>

<p>Aggregate Knowledge released Postgres HyperLogLog, which is a new Postgres datatype hll that strikes a balance between HyperLogLog and a simple set. This data type solves the problem of calculating uniques for a given data set efficiently both in performance and storage.</p>

<p><em>The above is still one of my favorite extensions that most of the world doesn&rsquo;t know about</em></p>

<h4><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/02/13/How-I-Work-With-Postgres/?utm_source=craigkerstiens&amp;utm_medium=bloga">How I Work with Postgres &ndash; Psql, My PostgreSQL Admin</a></h4>

<p>A common question for anyone new or even experienced with Postgres is whats the best editor out there? Most when they are asking this are asking for a GUI editor, this post highlights much of the power in the CLI &lsquo;psql&rsquo; editor.</p>

<h3>A mix of notable entries</h3>

<h4><a href="http://postgresweekly.com/issues/6">Issue 6</a> <a href="http://blog.blackwinghq.com/2013/04/08/2/?utm_source=craigkerstiens&amp;utm_medium=blog">Dissecting PostgreSQL CVE-2013-1899</a></h4>

<p>After the heavily publicized and very serious security vulnerability was patched last week Blackwing intelligence took the chance to dig in. Read more on the details of the vulnerability such as what damage can be done and the basics of how its exploitable.</p>

<h4><a href="http://postgresweekly.com/issues/16">Issue 16</a> <a href="http://www.justin.tv/sfpug/b/419326732?utm_source=craigkerstiens&amp;utm_medium=blog">Tom Lane Explains Query Planner video</a></h4>

<p>Tom Lane, one of the major contributors to Postgres and on the Postgres core team, was in San Francisco last week and gave a talk at the SF Postgres Users Group. Here&rsquo;s the video from the talk where Tom explains the innards of the PostgreSQL query planner. Whether you&rsquo;re a noob or a knowledgable Postgres user this is a must watch.</p>

<h4><a href="http://postgresweekly.com/issues/35">Issue 35</a> <a href="http://www.chesnok.com/daily/2013/11/06/top-10-psql-commands-i-use/">Top 10 psql ‘\’ commands I use</a></h4>

<p>Psql is incredibly powerful, but the list of options within it can be overwhelming. Heres a straight forward list of @selenamarie’s top 10 commands.</p>

<h4><a href="http://postgresweekly.com/issues/38">Issue 38</a> <a href="http://www.chesnok.com/daily/2013/11/13/everyday-postgres-tuning-a-brand-new-server-the-10-minute-edition/?utm_source=craigkerstiens&amp;utm_medium=blog">Everyday Postgres: Tuning a brand-new server &ndash; the 10 minute edition</a></h4>

<p>After a fresh install, there are probably a few knobs you want to tweak on Postgres. If you’re new to doing this, it can be a bit overwhelming. Here’s a quick primer on tuning a brand new server to be more properly configured.</p>

<h3><a href="http://postgresweekly.com/issues/51">And the latest issue</a></h3>

<p>Which highlights a wealth of information on <a href="http://postgresweekly.com/issues/51">jsonb</a>, and a bit of various knowledge touching on <a href="http://hans.io/blog/2014/03/25/postgresql_cluster/index.html?utm_source=craigkerstiens&amp;utm_medium=blog">cluster</a>, <a href="http://practiceovertheory.com/blog/2013/07/12/recursive-query-is-recursive/?utm_source=craigkerstiens&amp;utm_medium=blog">recursive queries with CTEs</a>, and <a href="http://www.davidhampgonsalves.com/Postgres-ranges/?utm_source=craigkerstiens&amp;utm_medium=blog">range types</a>.</p>

<h3>In conclusion</h3>

<p>What did you like? Any favorites I missed? What would you like to see more of? Let me know <a href="http://www.twitter.com/craigkerstiens">@craigkerstiens</a> or at <a href="mailto:craig.kerstiens@gmail.com">craig.kerstiens at gmail.com</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PostgreSQL 9.4 - Looking up (with JSONB and logical decoding)]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/03/24/Postgres-9.4-Looking-up/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/03/24/Postgres-9.4-Looking-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a few weeks back I wrote a article discussing many of the things that were likely to miss making the <a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/02/15/PostgreSQL-9.4-What-I-Wanted/">9.4 PostgreSQL release</a>. Since that post a few weeks ago the landscape has already changed, and much more for the positive.</p>

<p><em>The lesson here, is never count Postgres out</em>. As <a href="www.linuxinsider.com/story/Bruce-Momjian-PostrgreSQL-Prefers-the-Scenic-Route-80045.html">Bruce discussed in a recent interview</a>, Postgres is slow and steady, but much like the turtle can win the race.</p>

<p>So onto the actual features:</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>JSONB</h3>

<p>JSON has existed for a while in Postgres. Though the JSON that exists today simply validates that your text is valid JSON, then goes on to store it in a text field. This is fine, but not overly performant. If you do need some flexibility of your schema and performance without much effort then hstore may already work for you today, you can of course read more on this in an old post comparing <a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/07/03/hstore-vs-json/">hstore to json</a>.</p>

<p>But let&rsquo;s assume you do want JSON and a full document store, which is perfectly reasonable. Your option today is still best with the JSON datatype. And if you&rsquo;re retrieving full documents this is fine, however if you&rsquo;re searching/filtering on values within those documents then you need to take advantage of some functional indexing. You can do this some of the <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.3/static/functions-json.html">built-in operators</a> or with full <a href="https://postgres.heroku.com/blog/past/2013/6/5/javascript_in_your_postgres/">JS in Postgres</a>. This is a little more work, but also very possible to get good performance.</p>

<p>Finally, onto the perfect world, where JSON isn&rsquo;t just text in your database. For some time there&rsquo;s been a discussion around hstore and its future progress and of course the future of JSON in Postgres. These two worlds have finally heavily converged for PostgreSQL 9.4 giving you <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/message-id/E1WRpmB-0002et-MT@gemulon.postgresql.org">the best of both worlds</a>. With what was known as hstore2, by <a href="http://obartunov.livejournal.com/177247.html">The Russians</a> under the covers, and collective efforts on JSONB (Binary representation of JSON) which included all the JSON interfaces you&rsquo;d expect. We now have full document storage and awesome performance with little effort.</p>

<p>Digging in a little further, why does it matter that its a binary representation? Well under the covers building on the hstore functionality brings along some of the awesome index types in Postgres. Namely GIN and possibly in the future GIST. These indexes will automatically index all keys and values within a document, meaning you don&rsquo;t have to manually create individual functional indexes. Oh and they&rsquo;re <a href="http://thebuild.com/presentations/pg-as-nosql-pgday-fosdem-2013.pdf">fast and often small</a> on disk as well.</p>

<h3>Logical Decoding</h3>

<p>Logical replication was another feature that I talked about that was likely missing. Here there isn&rsquo;t the same positive news as JSONB, as there&rsquo;s not a 100% usable feature available. Yet there is a big silver lining in it. <a href="http://git.postgresql.org/gitweb/?p=postgresql.git;a=commitdiff;h=b89e151054a05f0f6d356ca52e3b725dd0505e53">Committed just over a week ago</a> was logical decoding. This means that we can decode the WAL (Write-Ahead-Log) into logical changes. In layman&rsquo;s terms this means something thats unreadable to anything but Postgres (and version dependent in cases) can be intrepretted to a series of <code>INSERT</code>s, <code>UPDATE</code>s, <code>DELETE</code>s, etc. With logical commands you could then start to get closer to cross version upgrades and eventually multi-master.</p>

<p>With this commit it doesn&rsquo;t mean all the pieces are there in the core of Postgres today. What it does mean is the part thats required of the Postgres core is done. The rest of this, which includes sending the logical replication stream somewhere, and then having something apply it can be developed fully as an extension.</p>

<h3>In Conclusion</h3>

<p>Postgres 9.4 isn&rsquo;t 100% complete yet, as the commitfest is still going on. You can follow along on the <a href="www.postgresql.org/list/pgsql-hackers/2014-03/">postgres hackers mailing list</a> or on the <a href="https://commitfest.postgresql.org/">commitfest app</a> where you can follow specific patches or even chip in on reviewing. And of course I&rsquo;ll do my best to continue to highlight useful features here and surface them on <a href="http://www.postgresweekly.com">Postgres Weekly</a> as well.</p>

<!-- Begin MailChimp Signup Form -->


<p><link href="//cdn-images.mailchimp.com/embedcode/classic-081711.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"></p>



<div id="mc_embed_signup">
<form action="http://craigkerstiens.us5.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc&amp;id=dacc2c6d9a" method="post" id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <h2>Sign up to get weekly advice and content on Postgres</h2>
<div class="indicates-required"><span class="asterisk">*</span> indicates required</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
    <label for="mce-EMAIL">Email Address  <span class="asterisk">*</span>
</label>
    <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="required email" id="mce-EMAIL">
</div>
    <div id="mce-responses" class="clear">
        <div class="response" id="mce-error-response" style="display:none"></div>
        <div class="response" id="mce-success-response" style="display:none"></div>
    </div>    <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
    <div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;"><input type="text" name="b_0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc_dacc2c6d9a" tabindex="-1" value=""></div>
    <div class="clear"><input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button"></div>
</form>
</div>


<script type="text/javascript">
var fnames = new Array();var ftypes = new Array();fnames[0]='EMAIL';ftypes[0]='email';
try {
    var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    jqueryLoaded=true;
} catch(err) {
    var jqueryLoaded=false;
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
if (!jqueryLoaded) {
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = '//ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.4.4/jquery.min.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    if (script.readyState && script.onload!==null){
        script.onreadystatechange= function () {
              if (this.readyState == 'complete') mce_preload_check();
        }    
    }
}

var err_style = '';
try{
    err_style = mc_custom_error_style;
} catch(e){
    err_style = '#mc_embed_signup input.mce_inline_error{border-color:#6B0505;} #mc_embed_signup div.mce_inline_error{margin: 0 0 1em 0; padding: 5px 10px; background-color:#6B0505; font-weight: bold; z-index: 1; color:#fff;}';
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
var style= document.createElement('style');
style.type= 'text/css';
if (style.styleSheet) {
  style.styleSheet.cssText = err_style;
} else {
  style.appendChild(document.createTextNode(err_style));
}
head.appendChild(style);
setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);

var mce_preload_checks = 0;
function mce_preload_check(){
    if (mce_preload_checks>40) return;
    mce_preload_checks++;
    try {
        var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = 'http://downloads.mailchimp.com/js/jquery.form-n-validate.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    try {
        var validatorLoaded=jQuery("#fake-form").validate({});
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    mce_init_form();
}
function mce_init_form(){
    jQuery(document).ready( function($) {
      var options = { errorClass: 'mce_inline_error', errorElement: 'div', onkeyup: function(){}, onfocusout:function(){}, onblur:function(){}  };
      var mce_validator = $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").validate(options);
      $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").unbind('submit');//remove the validator so we can get into beforeSubmit on the ajaxform, which then calls the validator
      options = { url: 'http://craigkerstiens.us5.list-manage.com/subscribe/post-json?u=0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc&id=dacc2c6d9a&c=?', type: 'GET', dataType: 'json', contentType: "application/json; charset=utf-8",
                    beforeSubmit: function(){
                        $('#mce_tmp_error_msg').remove();
                        $('.datefield','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var txt = 'filled';
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        var bday = false;
                                        if (fields.length == 2){
                                            bday = true;
                                            fields[2] = {'value':1970};//trick birthdays into having years
                                        }
                                        if ( fields[0].value=='MM' && fields[1].value=='DD' && (fields[2].value=='YYYY' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else if ( fields[0].value=='' && fields[1].value=='' && (fields[2].value=='' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else {
                                            if (/\[day\]/.test(fields[0].name)){
                                                this.value = fields[1].value+'/'+fields[0].value+'/'+fields[2].value;                                           
                                            } else {
                                                this.value = fields[0].value+'/'+fields[1].value+'/'+fields[2].value;
                                            }
                                        }
                                    });
                            });
                        $('.phonefield-us','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        if ( fields[0].value.length != 3 || fields[1].value.length!=3 || fields[2].value.length!=4 ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else {
                                            this.value = 'filled';
                                        }
                                    });
                            });
                        return mce_validator.form();
                    }, 
                    success: mce_success_cb
                };
      $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').ajaxForm(options);
      
      
    });
}
function mce_success_cb(resp){
    $('#mce-success-response').hide();
    $('#mce-error-response').hide();
    if (resp.result=="success"){
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(resp.msg);
        $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').each(function(){
            this.reset();
        });
    } else {
        var index = -1;
        var msg;
        try {
            var parts = resp.msg.split(' - ',2);
            if (parts[1]==undefined){
                msg = resp.msg;
            } else {
                i = parseInt(parts[0]);
                if (i.toString() == parts[0]){
                    index = parts[0];
                    msg = parts[1];
                } else {
                    index = -1;
                    msg = resp.msg;
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            index = -1;
            msg = resp.msg;
        }
        try{
            if (index== -1){
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);            
            } else {
                err_id = 'mce_tmp_error_msg';
                html = '<div id="'+err_id+'" style="'+err_style+'"> '+msg+'</div>';
                
                var input_id = '#mc_embed_signup';
                var f = $(input_id);
                if (ftypes[index]=='address'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-addr1';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else if (ftypes[index]=='date'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-month';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else {
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index];
                    f = $().parent(input_id).get(0);
                }
                if (f){
                    $(f).append(html);
                    $(input_id).focus();
                } else {
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
        }
    }
}

</script>


<!--End mc_embed_signup-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tracking Month over Month Growth in SQL]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/02/26/Tracking-MoM-growth-in-SQL/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/02/26/Tracking-MoM-growth-in-SQL</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/3f1q2N2s2V0d0G2s1T01/Blank.jpg" style="float:right;margin-left:20px;"/> In analyzing a business I commonly look at reports that have two lenses, one is by doing various cohort analysis. The other is that I look for Month over Month or Week over Week or some other X over X growth in terms of a percentage. This second form of looking at data is relevant when you&rsquo;re in a SaaS business or essentially anythign that does recurring billing. In such a business focusing on your MRR and working on <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B003XVYKRW?tag=mypred-20">growing your MRR is how success can often be measured</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I&rsquo;ll jump write in, first lets assume you have some method of querying your revenue. In this case you may have some basic query similar to:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT date_trunc('month', mydate) as date, 
       sum(mymoney) as revenue
FROM foo
GROUP BY date
ORDER BY date ASC;
</code></pre>

<p>This should give you a nice clean result:</p>

<pre><code> date                   | revenue  
------------------------+----------
 2013-10-01 00:00:00+00 | 10000    
 2013-11-01 00:00:00+00 | 11000    
 2013-12-01 00:00:00+00 | 11500    
</code></pre>

<p>Now this is great, but the first thing I want to do is start to see what my percentage growth month over month is. Surprise, surprise, I can do this directly in SQL. To do so I&rsquo;ll use a <a href="http://postgresguide.com/tips/window.html">window function</a> and then use the <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.3/static/functions-window.html">lag function</a>. According to the Postgres docs</p>

<p><em>lag(value any [, offset integer [, default any ]]) same type as value returns value evaluated at the row that is offset rows before the current row within the partition; if there is no such row, instead return default. Both offset and default are evaluated with respect to the current row. If omitted, offset defaults to 1 and default to null</em></p>

<p>Essentially it orders it based on the <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.3/static/tutorial-window.html">window function</a> and then pulls in the value from the row before. So in action it looks something like:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT date_trunc('month', mydate) as date, 
       sum(mymoney) as revenue,
       lag(mymoney, 1) over w previous_month_revenue
FROM foo
WINDOW w as (order by date)
GROUP BY date
ORDER BY date ASC;
</code></pre>

<p>Combining to actually make it a bit more pretty (with some casting to a numeric and then formatting a bit) in terms of a percentage:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT date_trunc('month', mydate) as date, 
       sum(mymoney) as revenue,
       round((1.0 - (cast(mymoney as numeric) / lag(mymoney, 1) over w)) * 100, 1) myVal_growth
FROM foo
WINDOW w as (order by date)
GROUP BY date
ORDER BY date ASC;
</code></pre>

<p>And you finally get a nice clean output of your month over month growth directly <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B0043EWUQQ?tag=mypred-20">in SQL</a>:</p>

<pre><code> date                   | revenue  | growth
------------------------+----------+--------
 2013-10-01 00:00:00+00 | 10000    |   null 
 2013-11-01 00:00:00+00 | 11000    |   10.0 
 2013-12-01 00:00:00+00 | 11500    |   4.5 
</code></pre>

<!-- Begin MailChimp Signup Form -->


<p><link href="//cdn-images.mailchimp.com/embedcode/classic-081711.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"></p>



<div id="mc_embed_signup">
<form action="http://craigkerstiens.us5.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc&amp;id=dacc2c6d9a" method="post" id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <h2>Sign up to get weekly advice and content on Postgres</h2>
<div class="indicates-required"><span class="asterisk">*</span> indicates required</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
    <label for="mce-EMAIL">Email Address  <span class="asterisk">*</span>
</label>
    <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="required email" id="mce-EMAIL">
</div>
    <div id="mce-responses" class="clear">
        <div class="response" id="mce-error-response" style="display:none"></div>
        <div class="response" id="mce-success-response" style="display:none"></div>
    </div>    <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
    <div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;"><input type="text" name="b_0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc_dacc2c6d9a" tabindex="-1" value=""></div>
    <div class="clear"><input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button"></div>
</form>
</div>


<script type="text/javascript">
var fnames = new Array();var ftypes = new Array();fnames[0]='EMAIL';ftypes[0]='email';
try {
    var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    jqueryLoaded=true;
} catch(err) {
    var jqueryLoaded=false;
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
if (!jqueryLoaded) {
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = '//ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.4.4/jquery.min.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    if (script.readyState && script.onload!==null){
        script.onreadystatechange= function () {
              if (this.readyState == 'complete') mce_preload_check();
        }    
    }
}

var err_style = '';
try{
    err_style = mc_custom_error_style;
} catch(e){
    err_style = '#mc_embed_signup input.mce_inline_error{border-color:#6B0505;} #mc_embed_signup div.mce_inline_error{margin: 0 0 1em 0; padding: 5px 10px; background-color:#6B0505; font-weight: bold; z-index: 1; color:#fff;}';
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
var style= document.createElement('style');
style.type= 'text/css';
if (style.styleSheet) {
  style.styleSheet.cssText = err_style;
} else {
  style.appendChild(document.createTextNode(err_style));
}
head.appendChild(style);
setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);

var mce_preload_checks = 0;
function mce_preload_check(){
    if (mce_preload_checks>40) return;
    mce_preload_checks++;
    try {
        var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = 'http://downloads.mailchimp.com/js/jquery.form-n-validate.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    try {
        var validatorLoaded=jQuery("#fake-form").validate({});
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    mce_init_form();
}
function mce_init_form(){
    jQuery(document).ready( function($) {
      var options = { errorClass: 'mce_inline_error', errorElement: 'div', onkeyup: function(){}, onfocusout:function(){}, onblur:function(){}  };
      var mce_validator = $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").validate(options);
      $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").unbind('submit');//remove the validator so we can get into beforeSubmit on the ajaxform, which then calls the validator
      options = { url: 'http://craigkerstiens.us5.list-manage.com/subscribe/post-json?u=0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc&id=dacc2c6d9a&c=?', type: 'GET', dataType: 'json', contentType: "application/json; charset=utf-8",
                    beforeSubmit: function(){
                        $('#mce_tmp_error_msg').remove();
                        $('.datefield','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var txt = 'filled';
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        var bday = false;
                                        if (fields.length == 2){
                                            bday = true;
                                            fields[2] = {'value':1970};//trick birthdays into having years
                                        }
                                        if ( fields[0].value=='MM' && fields[1].value=='DD' && (fields[2].value=='YYYY' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else if ( fields[0].value=='' && fields[1].value=='' && (fields[2].value=='' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else {
                                            if (/\[day\]/.test(fields[0].name)){
                                                this.value = fields[1].value+'/'+fields[0].value+'/'+fields[2].value;                                           
                                            } else {
                                                this.value = fields[0].value+'/'+fields[1].value+'/'+fields[2].value;
                                            }
                                        }
                                    });
                            });
                        $('.phonefield-us','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        if ( fields[0].value.length != 3 || fields[1].value.length!=3 || fields[2].value.length!=4 ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else {
                                            this.value = 'filled';
                                        }
                                    });
                            });
                        return mce_validator.form();
                    }, 
                    success: mce_success_cb
                };
      $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').ajaxForm(options);
      
      
    });
}
function mce_success_cb(resp){
    $('#mce-success-response').hide();
    $('#mce-error-response').hide();
    if (resp.result=="success"){
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(resp.msg);
        $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').each(function(){
            this.reset();
        });
    } else {
        var index = -1;
        var msg;
        try {
            var parts = resp.msg.split(' - ',2);
            if (parts[1]==undefined){
                msg = resp.msg;
            } else {
                i = parseInt(parts[0]);
                if (i.toString() == parts[0]){
                    index = parts[0];
                    msg = parts[1];
                } else {
                    index = -1;
                    msg = resp.msg;
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            index = -1;
            msg = resp.msg;
        }
        try{
            if (index== -1){
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);            
            } else {
                err_id = 'mce_tmp_error_msg';
                html = '<div id="'+err_id+'" style="'+err_style+'"> '+msg+'</div>';
                
                var input_id = '#mc_embed_signup';
                var f = $(input_id);
                if (ftypes[index]=='address'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-addr1';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else if (ftypes[index]=='date'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-month';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else {
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index];
                    f = $().parent(input_id).get(0);
                }
                if (f){
                    $(f).append(html);
                    $(input_id).focus();
                } else {
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
        }
    }
}

</script>


<!--End mc_embed_signup-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PostgreSQL 9.4 - What I was hoping for]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/02/15/PostgreSQL-9.4-What-I-Wanted/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/02/15/PostgreSQL-9.4-What-I-Wanted</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Theres no doubt that the <a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/02/02/Examining-PostgreSQL-9.4/">9.4 release</a> of PostgreSQL will have some great improvements. However, for all of the improvements it delivering it had the promise of being perhaps the most impactful release of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B008IGIKY6?tag=mypred-20">Postgres</a> yet. Several of the features that would have given it my stamp of best release in at least 5 years are now already not making it and a few others are still on the border. Here&rsquo;s a look at few of the things that were hoped for and not to be at least until another 18 months.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Upsert</h3>

<p>Upsert, merge, whatever you want to call it, this is been a sore hole for sometime now. Essentially this is insert based on this ID or if that key already exists update other values. This was something being worked on pretty early on in this release, and throughout the process continuing to make progress. Yet as progress was made so were exteneded discussions about syntax, approach, etc. In the end two differing views on how it should be implemented have the patch still sitting there with other thoughts on an implementation but not code ready to commit.</p>

<p>At the same time I&rsquo;ll acknowledge upsert as a hard problem to address. The locking and concurrency issues are non-trivial, but regardless of those having this in there mostly kills the final argument for anyone to chose MySQL.</p>

<h3>Better JSON</h3>

<p>JSON is Postgres is super flexible, powerful, and <strong>generally slow</strong>. Postgres does validation and some parsing of JSON, but without something like <a href="https://postgres.heroku.com/blog/past/2013/6/5/javascript_in_your_postgres/">PLV8</a>, or <a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/05/29/postgres-indexes-expression-or-functional-indexes/">functional indexes</a> you may not get great performance. This is because under the covers the JSON is represented as text and as a result many of the more powerful indexes that could lend benefit, such as GIN or GIST, simply don&rsquo;t apply here.</p>

<p>As a related effort to this <a href="http://postgresguide.com/sexy/hstore.html">hstore</a>, the key/value store, is working on being updated. This new support will add types and nesting making it much more usable overall. However the syntax and matching of how JSON functions isn&rsquo;t guranteed to be part of it. The proposal and actually work is still there and not rejected yet, but looks heavily at risk. Backing a new binary representation of JSON with hstore 2 would deliver so many benefits further building upon the foundation of hstore, JSON, PLV8 that exists today for Postgres.</p>

<h3>apt-get for your extensions</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m almost not even sure where to start with this one. The notion within a Postgres community is that packaging for distros is super simple and extensions should just be packaged for them. Then there&rsquo;s <a href="http://pgxn.org/">PGXN</a> the Postgres extension network where you can download and compile and muck with annoying settings to get extensions to build. This proposal would have delivered a built in installer much like NPM or rubygems or PyPi and the ability for someone to simply say install extension from this centralized repository. No, it was setting out to solve the issue of having a single repository but would make it much easier for people to run one.</p>

<p>For all the awesome-ness that exists in extensions such as <a href="http://tapoueh.org/blog/2013/02/25-postgresql-hyperloglog">HyperLogLog</a>, <a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2012/10/18/connecting_to_redis_from_postgres/">foreign data wrappers</a>, <a href="http://madlib.net/">madlib</a> theres hundreds of other extensions that could be written and be valuable. They don&rsquo;t even all require C, they could fully exist in JavaScript with PLV8. Yet I&rsquo;m on the fence encouraging people to write such because if no one uses it then much of the point in the reusability of an extension is lost. Here&rsquo;s hoping that there&rsquo;s a change of opinion in the future that packaging is a solved problem and that creating an ecosystem for others to contribute to the Postgres world without knowing C is a positive thing.</p>

<h3>Logical replication</h3>

<p>When I first heard this might have some shot at making it in 9.4 I was shocked. This is something that while some may not take notice of I&rsquo;ve felt pain of for many years. Logical replication means in short enabling upgrades across PostgreSQL versions without a dump and restore, but even more so laying the ground work for more complicated architectures like perhaps multi-master. Yes, even with logical replication in theres still plenty of work to do, but having the groundwork laid goes a long way. There are options for it today with third party tools, but the management of these is painful at best.</p>

<h3>In conclusion</h3>

<p>The positive of this one is that the building blocks are in and its continuing to make progress. Its just that we&rsquo;ll have to wait about 18 months before the release of PostgreSQL 9.5 before its in our hands.</p>

<!-- Begin MailChimp Signup Form -->


<p><link href="//cdn-images.mailchimp.com/embedcode/classic-081711.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"></p>



<div id="mc_embed_signup">
<form action="http://craigkerstiens.us5.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc&amp;id=dacc2c6d9a" method="post" id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <h2>Sign up to get weekly advice and content on Postgres</h2>
<div class="indicates-required"><span class="asterisk">*</span> indicates required</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
    <label for="mce-EMAIL">Email Address  <span class="asterisk">*</span>
</label>
    <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="required email" id="mce-EMAIL">
</div>
    <div id="mce-responses" class="clear">
        <div class="response" id="mce-error-response" style="display:none"></div>
        <div class="response" id="mce-success-response" style="display:none"></div>
    </div>    <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
    <div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;"><input type="text" name="b_0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc_dacc2c6d9a" tabindex="-1" value=""></div>
    <div class="clear"><input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button"></div>
</form>
</div>


<script type="text/javascript">
var fnames = new Array();var ftypes = new Array();fnames[0]='EMAIL';ftypes[0]='email';
try {
    var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    jqueryLoaded=true;
} catch(err) {
    var jqueryLoaded=false;
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
if (!jqueryLoaded) {
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = '//ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.4.4/jquery.min.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    if (script.readyState && script.onload!==null){
        script.onreadystatechange= function () {
              if (this.readyState == 'complete') mce_preload_check();
        }    
    }
}

var err_style = '';
try{
    err_style = mc_custom_error_style;
} catch(e){
    err_style = '#mc_embed_signup input.mce_inline_error{border-color:#6B0505;} #mc_embed_signup div.mce_inline_error{margin: 0 0 1em 0; padding: 5px 10px; background-color:#6B0505; font-weight: bold; z-index: 1; color:#fff;}';
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
var style= document.createElement('style');
style.type= 'text/css';
if (style.styleSheet) {
  style.styleSheet.cssText = err_style;
} else {
  style.appendChild(document.createTextNode(err_style));
}
head.appendChild(style);
setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);

var mce_preload_checks = 0;
function mce_preload_check(){
    if (mce_preload_checks>40) return;
    mce_preload_checks++;
    try {
        var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = 'http://downloads.mailchimp.com/js/jquery.form-n-validate.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    try {
        var validatorLoaded=jQuery("#fake-form").validate({});
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    mce_init_form();
}
function mce_init_form(){
    jQuery(document).ready( function($) {
      var options = { errorClass: 'mce_inline_error', errorElement: 'div', onkeyup: function(){}, onfocusout:function(){}, onblur:function(){}  };
      var mce_validator = $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").validate(options);
      $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").unbind('submit');//remove the validator so we can get into beforeSubmit on the ajaxform, which then calls the validator
      options = { url: 'http://craigkerstiens.us5.list-manage.com/subscribe/post-json?u=0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc&id=dacc2c6d9a&c=?', type: 'GET', dataType: 'json', contentType: "application/json; charset=utf-8",
                    beforeSubmit: function(){
                        $('#mce_tmp_error_msg').remove();
                        $('.datefield','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var txt = 'filled';
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        var bday = false;
                                        if (fields.length == 2){
                                            bday = true;
                                            fields[2] = {'value':1970};//trick birthdays into having years
                                        }
                                        if ( fields[0].value=='MM' && fields[1].value=='DD' && (fields[2].value=='YYYY' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else if ( fields[0].value=='' && fields[1].value=='' && (fields[2].value=='' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else {
                                            if (/\[day\]/.test(fields[0].name)){
                                                this.value = fields[1].value+'/'+fields[0].value+'/'+fields[2].value;                                           
                                            } else {
                                                this.value = fields[0].value+'/'+fields[1].value+'/'+fields[2].value;
                                            }
                                        }
                                    });
                            });
                        $('.phonefield-us','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        if ( fields[0].value.length != 3 || fields[1].value.length!=3 || fields[2].value.length!=4 ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else {
                                            this.value = 'filled';
                                        }
                                    });
                            });
                        return mce_validator.form();
                    }, 
                    success: mce_success_cb
                };
      $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').ajaxForm(options);
      
      
    });
}
function mce_success_cb(resp){
    $('#mce-success-response').hide();
    $('#mce-error-response').hide();
    if (resp.result=="success"){
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(resp.msg);
        $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').each(function(){
            this.reset();
        });
    } else {
        var index = -1;
        var msg;
        try {
            var parts = resp.msg.split(' - ',2);
            if (parts[1]==undefined){
                msg = resp.msg;
            } else {
                i = parseInt(parts[0]);
                if (i.toString() == parts[0]){
                    index = parts[0];
                    msg = parts[1];
                } else {
                    index = -1;
                    msg = resp.msg;
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            index = -1;
            msg = resp.msg;
        }
        try{
            if (index== -1){
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);            
            } else {
                err_id = 'mce_tmp_error_msg';
                html = '<div id="'+err_id+'" style="'+err_style+'"> '+msg+'</div>';
                
                var input_id = '#mc_embed_signup';
                var f = $(input_id);
                if (ftypes[index]=='address'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-addr1';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else if (ftypes[index]=='date'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-month';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else {
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index];
                    f = $().parent(input_id).get(0);
                }
                if (f){
                    $(f).append(html);
                    $(input_id).focus();
                } else {
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
        }
    }
}

</script>


<!--End mc_embed_signup-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I hack email]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/02/07/my-email-hacks/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/02/07/my-email-hacks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a conversation with <a href="http://www.twitter.com/alexbaldwin">@alexbaldwin</a> yesterday the topic of email came up, with each of us quickly diving into various observations, how its both awesome and a great form of communication/engagement, how most people still do it really bad. Alex has some good experience with it with hack design having over 100,000 subscribers. A tangent in an entirely unrelated meeting with <a href="http://www.twitter.com/mschoening">@mschoening</a> and others it was suggested instead of emailing a list to send out a ton of individual emails instead. Both of these reminded me that email is incredibly powerful, but taking advantage of its power has to be intentional.</p>

<p>This is not about ways to get to inbox 0 or better manage your inflow of emails. Rather its about how to get the maximum output out of emails that you send, or minimum output depending on what you prefer.</p>

<!--more-->


<p></p>

<h3>1 email to 100 vs. 100 emails to 1</h3>

<p>This is perhaps my favorite approach to get more efficient feedback and also know how broad an impact something has. Most smaller companies or groups within a company have a mailing list thats <a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#105;&#x6c;&#116;&#111;&#x3a;&#97;&#x6c;&#x6c;&#64;&#x79;&#x6f;&#x75;&#114;&#x63;&#111;&#x6d;&#x70;&#97;&#x6e;&#121;&#x2e;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;">&#x61;&#x6c;&#108;&#64;&#121;&#x6f;&#117;&#114;&#x63;&#111;&#x6d;&#112;&#97;&#110;&#x79;&#46;&#x63;&#111;&#x6d;</a> or <a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#x3a;&#x6f;&#x75;&#x72;&#103;&#x72;&#x6f;&#x75;&#x70;&#x40;&#109;&#x79;&#x63;&#111;&#109;&#x70;&#x61;&#110;&#x79;&#x2e;&#x63;&#x6f;&#x6d;&#x2e;">&#111;&#117;&#114;&#103;&#x72;&#x6f;&#117;&#112;&#64;&#x6d;&#121;&#x63;&#x6f;&#x6d;&#112;&#97;&#110;&#121;&#x2e;&#99;&#x6f;&#x6d;&#x2e;</a> When people want to communicate out to the entire list its a great mechanism, however when you want feedback from the entire company its not a great mechanism.</p>

<p>The reason being is that most people will know how many are on that list and assume that someone else will pick it up. This concept is fairly common in physical settings known as the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bystander_effect">bystander effect</a>, stating that individuals often do not offer up help to a victim when there are other bystanders preset.</p>

<p>Finally in certain situations you&rsquo;ll want to hear the same thing 100 times. Hearing something once doesn&rsquo;t represent how much others echo that. You&rsquo;ll only see so many +1s on a thread, getting 100 individual responses ensure you get not only the breadth of responses but amplitude of them.</p>

<p><em>FWIW, I ran a test of this sending an email to essentially all@heroku, then an individualized email in a similar form. The one directly addressed to people received 5x response as well as more thorough responses in the same time frame</em></p>

<h3>Scaling requests for input</h3>

<p>The issue that typically exists with the above is that you don&rsquo;t want 100 responses from 100 people most of the time. Most of the time you want feedback from 2 or 3, then feedback from 4 or 5, then smaller feedback or revision from the rest of that 100. This is actually how I craft blog posts, I start with broad messaging/theming. At that level there&rsquo;s truly 100 different directions it could go, that kind of input it not helpful when I have to narrow it down to a single one. When collecting product/roadmap input it can be helpful. Knowing which of the two I&rsquo;m aiming for is critical in deciding a method.</p>

<h3>Being explicit about the before and the ask</h3>

<p>On the note of crafting a blog post I do usually start with a request from 2 or 3 to get general direction. This takes the effect of, is this interesting? From here though theres still further refinement. The next phase is, does this flow, does it make sense? Here having a broader list is helpful so usually it&rsquo;ll hit around 4 to 5 people. Finally I&rsquo;ll revert to the 1 email to 100 people on a mailing list asking for grammar input because mine is crap. Here I don&rsquo;t mind the bystander effect because I want people to intentionally filter so it works well.</p>

<p>The key at each step of the process is being extremely clear of whats already been done. With a blog post as an example&hellip; If I don&rsquo;t explain the process of people having reviewed and set the goals and some consensus that it meets them, that several have been over it for flow, and that what I&rsquo;m looking for now which is grammar feedback.</p>

<h3>Circulating through people</h3>

<p>Email and requests are a time burden on people. I commonly diversify and circle through a set of people. Much in the same way I reach out to people to have drinks or coffee every so often I am to not do the same person every week and only that person with the exception of my wife.</p>

<p>Having more of a rotating basis of getting through people increases their excited-ness to provide input. If I&rsquo;m always going back to the same people they may feel slightly drained by my constant requests, and quite rightfully so. At the same time the input is good, but diversifying where you receive it gives a broader perspective.</p>

<h3>Delayed sending</h3>

<p>This is one that may be a little more obvious to people. But sending an email to slow down a thread, not seem over eager, or for whatever other reason you may have is hugely useful. There&rsquo;s really two tools I look to here: 1. <a href="http://www.boomeranggmail.com/referral_download.html?ref=vsz82">Boomerang</a> and 2. <a href="http://www.yesware.com">Yesware</a>. Both have slightly different benefits. Boomerang with a much simpler interface, Yesware better integration with Salesforce. Regardless of which you choose, if you ever want to type and email but send it at some point later one of these is critical.</p>

<h3>Fin.</h3>

<p>While this list is less of a defined process and more of a collection of random processes, several of these I&rsquo;d be much less effective without, and the collection of all makes getting appropriate reactions from email incredibly useful. I&rsquo;d love to hear what hacks you use to elicit positive impact from the emails you receive, as always if you have feedback please drop me a note.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Examining Postgres 9.4 - A first look]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/02/02/Examining-PostgreSQL-9.4/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/02/02/Examining-PostgreSQL-9.4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/B008IGIKY6?tag=mypred-20">PostgreSQL</a> is currently entering its final commit fest. While its still going, which means there could still be more great features to come, we can start to take a look at what you can expect from it now. This release seems to bring a lot of minor increments versus some bigger highlights of previous ones. At the same time there&rsquo;s still a lot on the bubble that may or may not make it which could entirely change the shape of this one. For a peek back of some of the past ones:</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Highlights of 9.2</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/01/10/more-on-postgres-performance/">pg_stat_statements</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.postgresql.org/wiki/Index-only_scans">Index only scans</a></li>
<li><a href="https://postgres.heroku.com/blog/past/2012/12/6/postgres_92_now_available/#json_support">JSON Support</a></li>
<li><a href="https://postgres.heroku.com/blog/past/2012/12/6/postgres_92_now_available/#range_type_support">Range types</a></li>
<li>Huge performance improvements</li>
</ul>


<h3>Highlights of 9.3</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/08/05/a-look-at-FDWs/">Postgres foreign data wrapper</a></li>
<li><a href="https://postgres.heroku.com/blog/past/2013/9/9/postgres_93_now_available/#materialized_views">Materialized views</a></li>
<li>Checksums</li>
</ul>


<h2>On to 9.4</h2>

<p>With 9.4 instead of a simply list lets dive into a little deeper to the more noticable one.</p>

<h3>pg_prewarm</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ll lead with one that those who need it should see huge gains (read larger apps that have a read replica they eventually may fail over to). Pg_prewarm will pre-warm your cache by loading data into memory. You may be interested in running <code>pg_prewarm</code> before bringing up a new Postgres DB or on a replica to keep it fresh.</p>

<p><em>Why it matters</em>  &ndash; If you have a read replica it won&rsquo;t have the same cache as the leader. This can work great as you can send queries to it and it&rsquo;ll optimize its own cache. However, if you&rsquo;re using it as a failover when you do have to failover you&rsquo;ll be running in a degraded mode while your cache warms up. Running <code>pg_pregwarm</code> against it on a periodic basis will make the experience when you do failover a much better one.</p>

<h3>Refresh materialized view concurrently</h3>

<p>Materialized views just came into Postgres in 9.3. The problem with them is they were largely unusable. This was because they 1. Didn&rsquo;t auto-refresh and 2. When you did refresh them it would lock the table while it ran the refresh making it unreadable during that time.</p>

<p>Materialized views are often most helpful on large reporting tables that can take some time to generate. Often such a query can take 10-30 minutes or even more to run. If you&rsquo;re unable to access said view during that time it greatly dampens their usefulness. Now running <code>REFRESH MATERIALIZED VIEW CONCURRENTLY foo</code> will regenerate it in the background so long as you have a unique index for the view.</p>

<h3>Ordered Set Aggregates</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m almost not really sure where to begin with this, the name itself almost makes me not want to take advantage. That said what this enables is if a few really awesome things you could do before that would require a few extra steps.</p>

<p>While there&rsquo;s plenty of aggregate functions in postgres getting something like percentile 95 or percentile 99 takes a little more effort. First you must order the entire set, then re-iterate over it to find the position you want. This is something I&rsquo;ve commonly done by using a window function coupled with a CTE. Now its much easier:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT percentile_disc(0.95) 
WITHIN GROUP (ORDER BY response_time) 
FROM pageviews;
</code></pre>

<p>In addition to varying percentile functions you can get quite a few others including:</p>

<ul>
<li>Mode</li>
<li>percentile_disc</li>
<li>percentile_cont</li>
<li>rank</li>
<li>dense_rank</li>
</ul>


<h3>More to come</h3>

<p>As I mentiend earlier the commit fest is still ongoing this means some things are still in flight. Here&rsquo;s a few that still offer some huge promise but haven&rsquo;t been committed yet:</p>

<ul>
<li>Insert on duplicate key or better known as Upsert</li>
<li>HStore 2 &ndash; various improvements to HStore</li>
<li>JSONB &ndash; Binary format of JSON built on top of HStore</li>
<li>Logical replication &ndash; this one looks like some pieces will make it, but not a wholey usable implementation.</li>
</ul>


<!-- Begin MailChimp Signup Form -->


<p><link href="//cdn-images.mailchimp.com/embedcode/classic-081711.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"></p>



<div id="mc_embed_signup">
<form action="http://craigkerstiens.us5.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc&amp;id=dacc2c6d9a" method="post" id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <h2>Sign up to get weekly advice and content on Postgres</h2>
<div class="indicates-required"><span class="asterisk">*</span> indicates required</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
    <label for="mce-EMAIL">Email Address  <span class="asterisk">*</span>
</label>
    <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="required email" id="mce-EMAIL">
</div>
    <div id="mce-responses" class="clear">
        <div class="response" id="mce-error-response" style="display:none"></div>
        <div class="response" id="mce-success-response" style="display:none"></div>
    </div>    <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
    <div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;"><input type="text" name="b_0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc_dacc2c6d9a" tabindex="-1" value=""></div>
    <div class="clear"><input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button"></div>
</form>
</div>


<script type="text/javascript">
var fnames = new Array();var ftypes = new Array();fnames[0]='EMAIL';ftypes[0]='email';
try {
    var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    jqueryLoaded=true;
} catch(err) {
    var jqueryLoaded=false;
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
if (!jqueryLoaded) {
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = '//ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.4.4/jquery.min.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    if (script.readyState && script.onload!==null){
        script.onreadystatechange= function () {
              if (this.readyState == 'complete') mce_preload_check();
        }    
    }
}

var err_style = '';
try{
    err_style = mc_custom_error_style;
} catch(e){
    err_style = '#mc_embed_signup input.mce_inline_error{border-color:#6B0505;} #mc_embed_signup div.mce_inline_error{margin: 0 0 1em 0; padding: 5px 10px; background-color:#6B0505; font-weight: bold; z-index: 1; color:#fff;}';
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
var style= document.createElement('style');
style.type= 'text/css';
if (style.styleSheet) {
  style.styleSheet.cssText = err_style;
} else {
  style.appendChild(document.createTextNode(err_style));
}
head.appendChild(style);
setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);

var mce_preload_checks = 0;
function mce_preload_check(){
    if (mce_preload_checks>40) return;
    mce_preload_checks++;
    try {
        var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = 'http://downloads.mailchimp.com/js/jquery.form-n-validate.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    try {
        var validatorLoaded=jQuery("#fake-form").validate({});
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    mce_init_form();
}
function mce_init_form(){
    jQuery(document).ready( function($) {
      var options = { errorClass: 'mce_inline_error', errorElement: 'div', onkeyup: function(){}, onfocusout:function(){}, onblur:function(){}  };
      var mce_validator = $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").validate(options);
      $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").unbind('submit');//remove the validator so we can get into beforeSubmit on the ajaxform, which then calls the validator
      options = { url: 'http://craigkerstiens.us5.list-manage.com/subscribe/post-json?u=0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc&id=dacc2c6d9a&c=?', type: 'GET', dataType: 'json', contentType: "application/json; charset=utf-8",
                    beforeSubmit: function(){
                        $('#mce_tmp_error_msg').remove();
                        $('.datefield','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var txt = 'filled';
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        var bday = false;
                                        if (fields.length == 2){
                                            bday = true;
                                            fields[2] = {'value':1970};//trick birthdays into having years
                                        }
                                        if ( fields[0].value=='MM' && fields[1].value=='DD' && (fields[2].value=='YYYY' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else if ( fields[0].value=='' && fields[1].value=='' && (fields[2].value=='' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else {
                                            if (/\[day\]/.test(fields[0].name)){
                                                this.value = fields[1].value+'/'+fields[0].value+'/'+fields[2].value;                                           
                                            } else {
                                                this.value = fields[0].value+'/'+fields[1].value+'/'+fields[2].value;
                                            }
                                        }
                                    });
                            });
                        $('.phonefield-us','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        if ( fields[0].value.length != 3 || fields[1].value.length!=3 || fields[2].value.length!=4 ){
                                            this.value = '';
                                        } else {
                                            this.value = 'filled';
                                        }
                                    });
                            });
                        return mce_validator.form();
                    }, 
                    success: mce_success_cb
                };
      $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').ajaxForm(options);
      
      
    });
}
function mce_success_cb(resp){
    $('#mce-success-response').hide();
    $('#mce-error-response').hide();
    if (resp.result=="success"){
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(resp.msg);
        $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').each(function(){
            this.reset();
        });
    } else {
        var index = -1;
        var msg;
        try {
            var parts = resp.msg.split(' - ',2);
            if (parts[1]==undefined){
                msg = resp.msg;
            } else {
                i = parseInt(parts[0]);
                if (i.toString() == parts[0]){
                    index = parts[0];
                    msg = parts[1];
                } else {
                    index = -1;
                    msg = resp.msg;
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            index = -1;
            msg = resp.msg;
        }
        try{
            if (index== -1){
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);            
            } else {
                err_id = 'mce_tmp_error_msg';
                html = '<div id="'+err_id+'" style="'+err_style+'"> '+msg+'</div>';
                
                var input_id = '#mc_embed_signup';
                var f = $(input_id);
                if (ftypes[index]=='address'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-addr1';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else if (ftypes[index]=='date'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-month';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else {
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index];
                    f = $().parent(input_id).get(0);
                }
                if (f){
                    $(f).append(html);
                    $(input_id).focus();
                } else {
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
        }
    }
}

</script>


<!--End mc_embed_signup-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Where to go with developer content]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/01/28/where-to-go-developer-content/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-28T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/01/28/where-to-go-developer-content</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I wrote up some <a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/01/16/developer-marketing-where-to-start-with-content/">initial steps for getting started with marketing a developer</a> focused product. The short of it was quite trying to do &ldquo;marketing&rdquo; and just start putting out interesting material. A big part of this is sourcing material from your company&rsquo;s developers. From there you want to gradually shift it from simply interesting technical posts to things that align with your core beliefs and add value to your customers.</p>

<p>Perhaps the easiest way to do this is by highlighting some examples of it.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Teach them how to</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.tindie.com/">Tindie</a> is a marketplace focused on makers. Browsing their site is simply awesome, there&rsquo;s everything from fully <a href="https://www.tindie.com/products/browse/home/">built things</a> to raw supplies to let me <a href="https://www.tindie.com/supplies/">start hacking</a>. The biggest problem though is they don&rsquo;t tell me how to take advantage of so much on their site. Posts similar to New Relic&rsquo;s on how they made their <a href="http://blog.newrelic.com/2013/11/18/making-futurestack-badge/">awesome conference badges</a> with a ready made shopping list of components would both get me excited and teach me something I didn&rsquo;t know how to do prior.</p>

<p>Now a lot of this may seem obvious, but its not just about giving a how to. This doesn&rsquo;t belong in a readme or in product documentation. Instead the activity of regularly crafting relevant stories that stretch how people think about hardware hacking should be a top of mind focus. It also positions you as a thought leader within the space. Right now there is no thought leader for makers, and theres ample opportunity to be that.</p>

<h3>Timely content</h3>

<p>Chipmaker <a href="https://www.spark.io/">Spark.io</a> recently hugely capitalized on the <a href="http://gizmodo.com/google-just-bought-nest-for-3-2-billion-1500503899">Nest acquisition</a> by writing a post only days after of how you can build an <a href="http://blog.spark.io/2014/01/17/open-source-thermostat/">open source Nest for $70</a>. I suspect they didn&rsquo;t have such a post just lying around waiting for the acquisition and instead scrambled to get it all together almost as soon as it occurred.</p>

<p>Over time the opportunity will always present itself in some form to attach yourself to another story. Sometimes this can be related to a direct competitor, sometimes its simply tangential. Being willing to quickly invest time when an opportunity presents itself is key to taking advantage of those opportunities. But please don&rsquo;t let such opportunities be your only way of capturing attention, there should still be a steady beat and focus.</p>

<h3>Let your beliefs come out</h3>

<p>Nearly everytime I sit down with some founder or very early employee at a company the vibe and impression I get from them is an order of magnitude stronger than the company&rsquo;s public persona. At the root of every company trying to do something big is an acute focus on a problem with strong opinions about how to solve them. You don&rsquo;t win people over by giving middle of the road opinions.</p>

<p>Heroku&rsquo;s often been an example of being extremely opinionated. For a long time you found bits of this within our product such as with an ephermal filesystem – which in the long term enables scalability. Or with directing the separation of code and config – which helps reproducability for when things go wrong and spinning up new copies of your app.</p>

<p>Again the biggest problem with this opinionation wasn&rsquo;t that it existed, but that it wasn&rsquo;t talked about clearly or loudly enough. Its now much clearer and broader in the form of <a href="http://12factor.net/">12 Factor</a> which fully codifies those strong opinions which influence the product, but also has applicability outside of Heroku.</p>

<h3>All of the approaches</h3>

<p>Doing just one of the above really isn&rsquo;t enough. Having multiple types of content such as the above three allow you to be much more effective. Of course the way you manage them and distribute them changes based on the type of content, but more on that later.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rethinking the limits on relational databases]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/01/24/rethinking-limits-on-relational/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-24T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/01/24/rethinking-limits-on-relational</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Theres a lot of back and forth on NoSQL databases. The unfortunate part with all the back and forth and unclear definitions of NoSQL is that many of the valuable learnings are lost. This post isn&rsquo;t about the differences in NoSQL definitions, but rather some of the huge benefits that do exist in whats often grouped into the schema-less world that could easily be applied to the relational world.</p>

<h3>Forget migrations</h3>

<p>Perhaps the best thing about the idea of a schemaless database is that you can just push code and it works. Almost exactly five years ago Heroku shipped <code>git push heroku master</code> letting you simply push code from git and it just work. CouchDB and MongoDB have done similar for databases&hellip; you don&rsquo;t have to run <code>CREATE TABLE</code> or <code>ALTER TABLE</code> migrations before working with your database. There&rsquo;s something wonderful about just building and shipping your application without worrying about migrations.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>This is often viewed as a limitation of relational databases. Yet it doesn&rsquo;t really have to. You see even in schema-less database the relationships are still there, its just you&rsquo;re managing it at the application level. There&rsquo;s no reason higher level frameworks or ORMs couldn&rsquo;t handle the migration process. As it is today the process of adding a column to a relational database is quite straightforward in a sense where it doesn&rsquo;t introduce downtime and is capable of letting the developer still move quickly its just not automatically baked in.</p>

<pre><code># Assuming a column thats referenced doesn't exist
# Automatically execute relevant bits in your ORM
# This isn't code meant for you to run 

ALTER TABLE foo ADD COLUMN bar varchar(255); # This is near instant
# Set your default value in your ORM
UPDATE TABLE foo SET bar = 'DEFAULT VALUE' WHERE bar IS NULL;
ALTER TABLE foo ALTER COLUMN bar NOT NULL;
</code></pre>

<p>Having Rails/Django/(Framework of your choice) automatically notice the need for a column to exist and make appropriate modifications you could work with it the same way you would managing a document relation in your code. Sure this is a manual painful process today, but theres no reason this can&rsquo;t be fully handled by PostgreSQL or directly within an ORM .</p>

<h3>Documents</h3>

<p>The other really strong case for the MongoDB/CouchDB camp is document storage. In this case I&rsquo;m going to equate a document directly to a JSON object. JSON itself is a wonderfully simply model that works so well for portability, and having to convert it within your application layer is well just painful. Yes Postgres has a JSON datatype, and the JSON datatype is continuing to be adopted now by many other relational databases. <em>I was shocked to hear that DB2 is getting support for JSON myself, while I expect improvements to come to it JSON was not at the top of my list</em>.</p>

<p>And JSON does absolutely make sense as a data type within a column. But thats still a bit limiting as a full document store, what you want in those cases is any query result as a full JSON object. This is heavily undersold within Postgres that you can simply convert a full row to JSON with a <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.3/static/functions-json.html">single function</a> &ndash; <code>row_to_json</code>.</p>

<p>Again having higher level frameworks take full advantage so that under the covers you can have your strongly typed tables, but a flexibility to map them to flexible JSON objects makes a great deal of sense here.</p>

<h3>Out of the box interfaces</h3>

<p>This isn&rsquo;t a strict benefit of schema-less databases. Some schema-less databases have this more out of the box such as Couch where others less so. The concept of exposing a rest interface is not something new, and has been tried on top of relational databases a <a href="http://htsql.org/">few times over</a>. This is clearly something that does need to be delivered. The case for it is pretty clear, it reduces the work of people having to recreate admin screens and gives an easy onboarding process for noobs.</p>

<p>Unfortunately there&rsquo;s not clear progress on this today for Postgres or other relational databases. In contrast other databases are delivering on this front often from day one :/</p>

<h3>Where to</h3>

<p>Some of the shifts in schema-less or really in other databases in general are not so large they cannot be subsummed into a broader option. At the same time there are some strong merits such as the ones above which do take an active effort to deliver on expanding what is a &ldquo;relational database&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Where to start with developer content]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/01/16/developer-marketing-where-to-start-with-content/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-16T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2014/01/16/developer-marketing-where-to-start-with-content</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Commonly at developer focused companies the question from a marketing team will come up of &ldquo;How do we get content that developers find interesting&rdquo;? Or how can I get our developers to blog more? Or some other similar question. I general the question of creating content and engaging with developers is a very common one, and often theres a mismatch between what marketing wants to do and what developers appreciate.</p>

<h3>Stop marketing</h3>

<p>Forget trying to &ldquo;market&rdquo; to developers. Hopefully you at least have developers that believe in the product their building, if thats not the case then find a new product or a new team. If you&rsquo;ve got a product targetted at developers and a team that believes in it then you&rsquo;re already half way there to marketing it. Now back to the first point, forget trying to market it. Start with building some form of an audience, reputation, respect among other developers. This isn&rsquo;t done through ads, email marketing, SEO or any of that. Its done by creating content that developers find interesting, as a first step forget your product entirely, but don&rsquo;t worry we&rsquo;ll get there soon enough.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Sourcing content</h3>

<p>The first piece of it on finding content should actually be extremely simple. Typically engineers love sharing knowledge and information. At least once a week there&rsquo;s an email out to all the engineers of a truly interesting approach to something. This content is often not in a perfect form for external publication, but quite close. In particular Heroku has <a href="https://twitter.com/mmcgrana">one employee</a>, an early employee and now architect, that every email he sends to such a group I pull down and save for future reading. Another example of this was one of the Heroku founder Adam Wiggins, you can find many similar emails slightly cleaned up as blog posts on his own <a href="https://adam.heroku.com/">blog</a>.</p>

<p>Take these emails, find someone technical enough to clean them up and ship them. Your goals here are to simply build some level of connection with other developers. Now a lot of time these may not be in the right &ldquo;voice&rdquo; for your company blog. Thats quite fine, I&rsquo;m a strong proponent of letting developers create their own personalitiies. The place for the content then may not always be on the company blog. In general I find there&rsquo;s three groupings:</p>

<ul>
<li>Content for the company blog by an employee</li>
<li>Content for an individuals blog (the caveat here is they need to regularly create content &ndash; every 6 months doesnt cut it)</li>
<li>Content for an <a href="http://codeascraft.com/">engineering blog</a> (if you have enough of the above that blog infrequently this is a great home for it)</li>
</ul>


<h3>Don&rsquo;t worry about the product yet</h3>

<p>No really don&rsquo;t worry about pitching your product. There was an awesome piece on the <a href="http://insideintercom.io/new-features-usually-flop/">intercom blog talking about why most features fail</a> and how companies pitch the details versus the problem they solve. Though there was a hidden gem in there:</p>

<blockquote><p>Telling your customers something is a “ground up rewrite”, “HTML5 based”, “responsive” or anything like that will miss the mark unless you’re selling to developers.</p><footer><strong>[Des Traynor] [http://insideintercom.io/new-features-usually-flop/] [New Features Usually Flop]</strong></footer></blockquote>


<p>For companies targetting developers this actually works really well, as a developer I care about the how. Simply put its interesting. Another great example of this is <a href="http://blog.priceonomics.com/">priceonomics</a>. To be honest I only checked what they actually do in writing this post, but their posts I regularly find interesting.</p>

<h3>Whats next</h3>

<p>What do you want to know about? Creating a voice/brand, starting to pitch your product, content distribution? Let me know. A good about of my time is spent on these and happy to discuss further on whats valuable to others so we don&rsquo;t have to suffer through painful marketing. Let me know <a href="mailto:craig.kerstiens@gmail.com">craig.kerstiens@gmail.com</a> or <a href="http://www.twitter.com/craigkerstiens">@craigkerstiens</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The best Postgres feature you're not using – CTEs aka WITH clauses]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/11/18/best-postgres-feature-youre-not-using/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-18T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/11/18/best-postgres-feature-youre-not-using</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>SQL by default isn&rsquo;t typically friendly to dive into, and especially so if you&rsquo;re reading someone else&rsquo;s already created queries. For some reason most people throw out principles we follow in other languages <a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/07/29/documenting-your-postgres-database/">such as commenting</a> and composability just for SQL. I was recently reminded of a key feature in Postgres that most don&rsquo;t use by <a href="http://www.twitter.com/timonk">@timonk</a> highlighting it in his AWS Re:Invent Redshift talk. The simple feature actually makes SQL both readable and composable, and even for my own queries capable of coming back to them months later and understanding them, where previously they would not be.</p>

<p>The feature itself is known as CTEs or common table expressions, you may also here it referred to as <code>WITH</code> clauses. The general idea is that it allows you to create something somewhat equivilant to a view that only exists during that transaction. You can create multiple of these which then allow for clear building blocks and make it simple to follow what you&rsquo;re doing.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Lets take a look at a nice simple one:</p>

<pre><code>WITH users_tasks AS (
  SELECT 
         users.email,
         array_agg(tasks.name) as task_list,
         projects.title
  FROM
       users,
       tasks,
       project
  WHERE
        users.id = tasks.user_id
        projects.title = tasks.project_id
  GROUP BY
           users.email,
           projects.title
)
</code></pre>

<p>Using this I could now just append some basic other query on to the end that references this CTE <code>users_tasks</code>. Something akin to:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT *
FROM users_tasks;
</code></pre>

<p>But where it becomes more interesting is chaining these together. So while I have all tasks assigned to each user here, perhaps I want to then find which users are responsible for more than 50% of the tasks on a given project, thus being the bottleneck. To oversimplify this we could do it a couple of ways, total up the tasks for each project, and then total up the tasks for each user per project:</p>

<pre><code>total_tasks_per_project AS (
  SELECT 
         project_id,
         count(*) as task_count
  FROM tasks
  GROUP BY project_id
),

tasks_per_project_per_user AS (
  SELECT 
         user_id,
         project_id,
         count(*) as task_count
  FROM tasks
  GROUP BY user_id, project_id
),
</code></pre>

<p>Then we would want to combine and find the users that are now over that 50%:</p>

<pre><code>overloaded_users AS (
  SELECT tasks_per_project_per_user.user_id,

  FROM tasks_per_project_per_user,
       total_tasks_per_project
  WHERE tasks_per_project_per_user.task_count &gt; (total_tasks_per_project / 2)
)
</code></pre>

<p>Now as a final goal I&rsquo;d want to get a comma separated list of tasks of the overloaded users. So we&rsquo;re simply giong to join against that <code>overloaded_users</code> and our initial list of <code>users_tasks</code>. Putting it all together it looks somewhat long, but becomes much more readable. And as a bonus I layered in some comments.</p>

<pre><code>--- Created by Craig Kerstiens 11/18/2013
--- Query highlights users that have over 50% of tasks on a given project
--- Gives comma separated list of their tasks and the project


--- Initial query to grab project title and tasks per user
WITH users_tasks AS (
  SELECT 
         users.id as user_id,
         users.email,
         array_agg(tasks.name) as task_list,
         projects.title
  FROM
       users,
       tasks,
       project
  WHERE
        users.id = tasks.user_id
        projects.title = tasks.project_id
  GROUP BY
           users.email,
           projects.title
),

--- Calculates the total tasks per each project
total_tasks_per_project AS (
  SELECT 
         project_id,
         count(*) as task_count
  FROM tasks
  GROUP BY project_id
),

--- Calculates the projects per each user
tasks_per_project_per_user AS (
  SELECT 
         user_id,
         project_id,
         count(*) as task_count
  FROM tasks
  GROUP BY user_id, project_id
),

--- Gets user ids that have over 50% of tasks assigned
overloaded_users AS (
  SELECT tasks_per_project_per_user.user_id,

  FROM tasks_per_project_per_user,
       total_tasks_per_project
  WHERE tasks_per_project_per_user.task_count &gt; (total_tasks_per_project / 2)
)

SELECT 
       email,
       task_list,
       title
FROM 
     users_tasks,
     overloaded_users
WHERE
      users_tasks.user_id = overloaded_users.user_id
</code></pre>

<p>CTEs won&rsquo;t always be quite as performant as optimizing your SQL to be as concise as possible. In most cases I have seen performance differences smaller than a 2X difference, this tradeoff for readability is a nobrainer as far as I&rsquo;m concerned. And with time the Postgres optimizer should continue to get better about such performance.</p>

<p>As for the verbosity, yes I could have done this query in probably 10-15 lines of very concise SQL. Yet, most may not be able to understand it quickly if at all. Readability is huge when it comes to SQL to ensure its doing the right thing. SQL will almost always tell you an answer, it just may not be to the question you think you&rsquo;re asking. Ensuring your queries can be reasoned about is critical to ensuring accuracy and CTEs are one great way of accomplishing that.</p>

<!-- Begin MailChimp Signup Form -->


<p><link href="//cdn-images.mailchimp.com/embedcode/classic-081711.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"></p>



<div id="mc_embed_signup">
<form action="http://craigkerstiens.us5.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc&amp;id=dacc2c6d9a" method="post" id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
  <h2>Sign up to get weekly advice and content on Postgres</h2>
<div class="indicates-required"><span class="asterisk">*</span> indicates required</div>
<div class="mc-field-group">
  <label for="mce-EMAIL">Email Address  <span class="asterisk">*</span>
</label>
  <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="required email" id="mce-EMAIL">
</div>
  <div id="mce-responses" class="clear">
    <div class="response" id="mce-error-response" style="display:none"></div>
    <div class="response" id="mce-success-response" style="display:none"></div>
  </div>    <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
    <div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;"><input type="text" name="b_0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc_dacc2c6d9a" tabindex="-1" value=""></div>
    <div class="clear"><input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button"></div>
</form>
</div>


<script type="text/javascript">
var fnames = new Array();var ftypes = new Array();fnames[0]='EMAIL';ftypes[0]='email';
try {
    var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    jqueryLoaded=true;
} catch(err) {
    var jqueryLoaded=false;
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
if (!jqueryLoaded) {
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = '//ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/1.4.4/jquery.min.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    if (script.readyState && script.onload!==null){
        script.onreadystatechange= function () {
              if (this.readyState == 'complete') mce_preload_check();
        }    
    }
}

var err_style = '';
try{
    err_style = mc_custom_error_style;
} catch(e){
    err_style = '#mc_embed_signup input.mce_inline_error{border-color:#6B0505;} #mc_embed_signup div.mce_inline_error{margin: 0 0 1em 0; padding: 5px 10px; background-color:#6B0505; font-weight: bold; z-index: 1; color:#fff;}';
}
var head= document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0];
var style= document.createElement('style');
style.type= 'text/css';
if (style.styleSheet) {
  style.styleSheet.cssText = err_style;
} else {
  style.appendChild(document.createTextNode(err_style));
}
head.appendChild(style);
setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);

var mce_preload_checks = 0;
function mce_preload_check(){
    if (mce_preload_checks>40) return;
    mce_preload_checks++;
    try {
        var jqueryLoaded=jQuery;
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    var script = document.createElement('script');
    script.type = 'text/javascript';
    script.src = 'http://downloads.mailchimp.com/js/jquery.form-n-validate.js';
    head.appendChild(script);
    try {
        var validatorLoaded=jQuery("#fake-form").validate({});
    } catch(err) {
        setTimeout('mce_preload_check();', 250);
        return;
    }
    mce_init_form();
}
function mce_init_form(){
    jQuery(document).ready( function($) {
      var options = { errorClass: 'mce_inline_error', errorElement: 'div', onkeyup: function(){}, onfocusout:function(){}, onblur:function(){}  };
      var mce_validator = $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").validate(options);
      $("#mc-embedded-subscribe-form").unbind('submit');//remove the validator so we can get into beforeSubmit on the ajaxform, which then calls the validator
      options = { url: 'http://craigkerstiens.us5.list-manage.com/subscribe/post-json?u=0bb2ad96ec10236507971efdc&id=dacc2c6d9a&c=?', type: 'GET', dataType: 'json', contentType: "application/json; charset=utf-8",
                    beforeSubmit: function(){
                        $('#mce_tmp_error_msg').remove();
                        $('.datefield','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var txt = 'filled';
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        var bday = false;
                                        if (fields.length == 2){
                                            bday = true;
                                            fields[2] = {'value':1970};//trick birthdays into having years
                                        }
                                      if ( fields[0].value=='MM' && fields[1].value=='DD' && (fields[2].value=='YYYY' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                        this.value = '';
                      } else if ( fields[0].value=='' && fields[1].value=='' && (fields[2].value=='' || (bday && fields[2].value==1970) ) ){
                                        this.value = '';
                      } else {
                          if (/\[day\]/.test(fields[0].name)){
                                              this.value = fields[1].value+'/'+fields[0].value+'/'+fields[2].value;                         
                          } else {
                                              this.value = fields[0].value+'/'+fields[1].value+'/'+fields[2].value;
                                          }
                                      }
                                    });
                            });
                        $('.phonefield-us','#mc_embed_signup').each(
                            function(){
                                var fields = new Array();
                                var i = 0;
                                $(':text', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        fields[i] = this;
                                        i++;
                                    });
                                $(':hidden', this).each(
                                    function(){
                                        if ( fields[0].value.length != 3 || fields[1].value.length!=3 || fields[2].value.length!=4 ){
                                        this.value = '';
                      } else {
                          this.value = 'filled';
                                      }
                                    });
                            });
                        return mce_validator.form();
                    }, 
                    success: mce_success_cb
                };
      $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').ajaxForm(options);
      
      
    });
}
function mce_success_cb(resp){
    $('#mce-success-response').hide();
    $('#mce-error-response').hide();
    if (resp.result=="success"){
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
        $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(resp.msg);
        $('#mc-embedded-subscribe-form').each(function(){
            this.reset();
      });
    } else {
        var index = -1;
        var msg;
        try {
            var parts = resp.msg.split(' - ',2);
            if (parts[1]==undefined){
                msg = resp.msg;
            } else {
                i = parseInt(parts[0]);
                if (i.toString() == parts[0]){
                    index = parts[0];
                    msg = parts[1];
                } else {
                    index = -1;
                    msg = resp.msg;
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            index = -1;
            msg = resp.msg;
        }
        try{
            if (index== -1){
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);            
            } else {
                err_id = 'mce_tmp_error_msg';
                html = '<div id="'+err_id+'" style="'+err_style+'"> '+msg+'</div>';
                
                var input_id = '#mc_embed_signup';
                var f = $(input_id);
                if (ftypes[index]=='address'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-addr1';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else if (ftypes[index]=='date'){
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index]+'-month';
                    f = $(input_id).parent().parent().get(0);
                } else {
                    input_id = '#mce-'+fnames[index];
                    f = $().parent(input_id).get(0);
                }
                if (f){
                    $(f).append(html);
                    $(input_id).focus();
                } else {
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
                    $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
                }
            }
        } catch(e){
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').show();
            $('#mce-'+resp.result+'-response').html(msg);
        }
    }
}

</script>


<!--End mc_embed_signup-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tooling for Simple but Informative Emails]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/10/13/simple-but-informative-emails/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/10/13/simple-but-informative-emails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Emails are one of my favorite methods of communicating with users. Its works as a quick test for product validation. It works well at one->some->many-> all. Its still highly effective even as much noise as we receive in our inboxes. Over the years I&rsquo;ve tried a lot of email tools from custom built solutions, to newer entrants that help around drip actions (<a href="http://www.intercom.io">intercom.io</a> and <a href="http://www.customer.io">customer.io</a>), to more &ldquo;enterprise&rdquo; tools such as Marketo. While I have varying opinions on all of those, I still find myself coming back to a simple one off script setup to deliver clear concise emails.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Getting the Data</h3>

<p>The first step of any email is deciding what you want to do, but hopefully you know that already. The part that is usually a bit more effort is actually getting the list to send it to and formatting it appropriately. I usually opt for SQL. While the specifics of the query of course always vary it common follows a general structure:</p>

<pre><code>WITH initial_data AS (
  SELECT 
         email,
         app_name,
         information_about_app 
  FROM
       users,
       apps
  WHERE users.id = apps.user_id
    AND some_filter_to_limit_data
),

candidates_for_email AS ... --- likely to have additional CTEs

--- Finally I build up the list

SELECT email,
       array_to_string(array_agg(data_for_email), '
') --- an important note is to add a newline or not here depending on how you wish to format it
FROM candidates_for_email
GROUP BY email;
</code></pre>

<p>The query structure you&rsquo;ll want is first column email, second column whatever data you want to include in your email.</p>

<p>From here I usually create a dataclip of it. This makes it easy to allow my data to change over time. If I&rsquo;m testing an email for data over the last 7 days I just come back in 7 days and I have new data. It also lets me easily share and iterate on the data. The nice part is there&rsquo;s an easy way to click a button and get the data as a CSV which is what you want for sending.</p>

<p>Once you download the CSV you&rsquo;ll want to remove the header line as its not needed for the script.</p>

<h3>Sending the Mail</h3>

<p>To actually send the email you&rsquo;ll need this script, which is largely credited to <a href="http://www.twitter.com/leinweber">@leinweber</a>:</p>

<pre><code>require 'mail'
require 'csv'
FILE = ARGV[0]

Mail.defaults do
  delivery_method :smtp, {
    address: 'smtp address',
    port: 587,
    domain: 'gmail.com',
    user_name: 'craig.kerstiens@gmail.com',
    password: ENV.fetch('EMAIL_PASSWORD'),
    authentication: :plain,
    enable_starttls_auto: true
  }
end


def send_email(address, app)
  mail = Mail.new do
    to      address
    from    'Craig Kerstiens &lt;craig.kerstiens@gmail.com&gt;'
    subject "Your email subject in here"
    body    generate_body(app)
  end
end

def generate_body(app)
  %Q( 
Hi,

Your list of apps: 

#{app}

Various email content in here...

  )
end


CSV.parse(File.read(FILE)).each do |line|
  address = line[0]
  app     = line[1]
  m = send_email(address, app)
  puts m.to_s
  p m.deliver!

  puts
  puts
end
</code></pre>

<p><em>You&rsquo;ll want to make sure to export the PW of your email provider with EXPORT EMAIL_PASSWORD=pw_here</em></p>

<p>You can easily download this script from off of <a href="https://gist.github.com/craigkerstiens/6922897">Github&rsquo;s Gist</a>. I&rsquo;d recommend using an email service provider other than Gmail in sending your emails such as <a href="http://www.mailgun.com">mailgun</a> as they&rsquo;re built to handle sending a large amount of emails. Finally send your emails:</p>

<pre><code>ruby email.rb nameofyourfile.csv
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Disabling muting while typing in Google hangouts]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/09/12/disabling-muting-while-typing-in-hangouts/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/09/12/disabling-muting-while-typing-in-hangouts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Google hangouts is awesome, its my preferred method for most audio/video calls these days. When running a group call I often dial into a separate phone if I have a better phone available for the group. It also got around the annoyance that when you are typing google automatically mutes you. This for most people is pretty subpar. While dialing in to the hangout can still be nice, you don&rsquo;t have to do so to get rid of the annoying muting while typing. To fix such simply open up your terminal and run:</p>

<pre><code> defaults write com.google.googletalkplugind exps -string [\"-tm\"]
</code></pre>

<p><em>This clever hack discovered courtesy of <a href="http://www.twitter.com/timtyrrell">@timtyrrell</a> passed along to me by <a href="http://www.twitter.com/mattmanning">@mattmanning</a> and <a href="http://www.twitter.com/blakegentry">@blakegentry</a></em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Diving into Postgres JSON operators and functions]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/09/11/diving-into-postgres-json-operators/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/09/11/diving-into-postgres-json-operators</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just as <a href="https://postgres.heroku.com/blog/past/2013/9/9/postgres_93_now_available/">PostgreSQL 9.3</a> was coming out I had a need to take advantage of the JSON datatype and some of the <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.3/static/functions-json.html">operators and functions</a> within it. The use case was pretty simple, run a query across a variety of databases, then take the results and store them. We explored doing something more elaborate with the columns/values, but in the end just opted to save the entire result set as JSON then I could use the operators to explore it as desired.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the general idea in code (using sequel):</p>

<pre><code>result = r.connection { |c| c.fetch(self.query).all }
mymodel.results = result.to_json
</code></pre>

<!--more-->


<p>As the entire dataset was stored as some compressed JSON I needed to do a bit of manipulation to get it back into a form that was workable. Fortunately all the steps were fairly straightforward.</p>

<p>First you want to unnest each result from the json array, in my case this looked like:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT json_array_elements(result)
</code></pre>

<p>The above will unnest all of the array elements so I have an individual result as JSON. A real world example would look something similar to:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT json_array_elements(result) 
FROM query_results 
LIMIT 2;
      json_array_elements
</code></pre>

<hr />

<p> {&ldquo;column_name&rdquo;:&ldquo;data_in_here&rdquo;}
 {&ldquo;column_name_2&rdquo;:&ldquo;other_data_in_here&rdquo;}
(2 rows)</p>

<p>From here based on the query I would want to get some specific value. In this case I&rsquo;m going to search for the text key column_name_2:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT json_array_elements(result)-&gt;'column_name_2' 
FROM query_results 
LIMIT 1;

  json_array_elements  
-----------------------
 "other_data_in_here"
(1 rows)
</code></pre>

<p><em>One gotcha I encountered was when I wanted to search for some value or exclude some value&hellip; Expecting I could just compare the result of the above in a where statement I was sadly mistaken because the equals operator didn&rsquo;t translate.</em> My first attempt at fixing this was to cast in this form:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT json_array_elements(result)-&gt;'column_name_2'::text
</code></pre>

<p>The sad part is because of the operator the cast doesn&rsquo;t get applied as I&rsquo;d expect. Instead you&rsquo;ll want to do:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT (json_array_elements(result)-&gt;'column_name_2')::text
</code></pre>

<p>Of course theres plenty more you can do with the <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.3/static/functions-json.html">JSON operators in the new Postgres 9.3</a>. If you&rsquo;ve already got JSON in your application give them a look today. And while slightly worse, if you&rsquo;ve got JSON stored in a text field simply cast it with <code>::json</code> to begin using the operators.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Rule of Thirds - followup]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/08/13/rule-of-thirds/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/08/13/rule-of-thirds</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Several months back I wrote about how we do <a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/03/13/planning-and-prioritizing/">higher level, long term planning within the Heroku Postgres team</a>. If you haven&rsquo;t read the previous article please start there.</p>

<p>The exercise or rule of thirds is intended to be approximate prioritization and not a perfect science. Since that time I&rsquo;m familiar with some teams both in and out of Heroku who have attempted this exercise with varying levels of success. We&rsquo;ve now done this process 4 times within the team and after the most recent exercise attempted to take some time to internalize why its worked well, creating some more specifics about the process. Heres an attempt to provide even more clarity:</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Gather data ahead of time</h2>

<p>Its really common to have a list things to work on, but knowing the impact of those is commonly pure speculation. There may be some people that talk to customers, but even then its a subset of your actual customer base. Going into the exercise as much data you can have ahead of time on impact of features and specific problems helps. In our case we do this by:</p>

<ol>
<li>Surveying current customers and users</li>
<li>Surveying attriters</li>
<li>Engaging with customer facing teams to hear trends</li>
<li>Input from external parties such as analysts on trends</li>
</ol>


<h2>Allow for casual discussion</h2>

<p>We typically conduct our planning exercise at an offsite, this is a multi-day time of team bonding, planning, hacking. We intentionally schedule our planning excercise towards the end of the offsite. This allows us to have updates/presentations frmo the data we&rsquo;ve gathered and from those that are customer facing. Presentations are meant to be short and direct, discussion can flow casually after. This gets a lot of people on the same page at a smaller level and reduces the problem of too many cooks in the kitchen come time for the actual exercise.</p>

<h2>The rule of thirds</h2>

<h3>Creating the list</h3>

<p>Coming to the exercise itself&hellip; We begin by everyone writing a list of their ideas individually, this is meant to be a list of the features we want to place on the grid. At this point theres no prioritizing of difficulty or impact. In addition each list while individually created does not have to contain items that only pertain to you, its more a comprehensive list of all the things you can think of that may be important to do.</p>

<h3>Bucketing part 1</h3>

<p>Once individual lists are created you can then collectively or designate one or two people to clean it up. We do this in two forms:</p>

<ol>
<li>Removing duplicate items, which there should be several of.</li>
<li>Bucketing my a common/theme idea, this simply makes things more digestable</li>
</ol>


<p>If you&rsquo;re a big group of greater than 7 then it may be advisable to designate two people to do this exercise together. If a smaller group it can be manageable to coordinate collectively.</p>

<h3>Bucketing part 2</h3>

<p>Once you&rsquo;ve removed dupes, identified themes, and removed excess items (depending on your team size you&rsquo;ll find how many feels right &ndash; we aim an average of 5-6 per square for a team of 10) its then on to actually putting them on the grid. In the past we&rsquo;ve done this a variety of ways but our most recent process seemed to be quiet efficient. We gave each item 60 seconds, at the end of that minute wherever the item was it was left there. This forced some quick discussion on impact and difficulty but in the end left us at a very good hit rate without taking multiple hours to complete the exercise.</p>

<h3>Final pass</h3>

<p>We intentionally design it so that low effort and high impact is on the top right corner. Finally once everything is on there we allocate names to the tasks, and put boxes around items we&rsquo;re planning to do in the coming months. With boxes make it very clear of what we are doing as well as explicitly things we are not. The initials or names make it clear of how loaded down people are. If your name is on 3 tasks that are high difficulty, then you&rsquo;re likely over allocated.</p>

<p>At this point things usually fall out pretty quickly and we emerge with some rough roadmap that in retrospect we&rsquo;ve followed pretty accuately.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The missing PostgreSQL documentation]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/08/07/the-missing-postgresql-documentation/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/08/07/the-missing-postgresql-documentation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a couple of years I&rsquo;ve complained about the Postgres documentation and at the same time paraded it as one of the best sets of documentation I&rsquo;ve encountered. In many ways the reason I veer towards <a href="http://www.postgresql.org">Postgres</a> as well as <a href="http://www.python.org">Python</a> and <a href="http://www.djangoproject.com">Django</a> is the quality of their documentation. If you need to find details about something its documented, and more importantly well and thoroughly documented.</p>

<p>In large part I came to Python by happenstance through <a href="http://www.djangoproject.com">Django</a>, and Postgres through happenstance of an employer. Yet, Django was very little of an accident. The Django Tutorial got me a large part of what I needed to know and more excited about development than I had been in some time. Python has done some work at adding docs to make this even better, sadly its still very much needed for PostgreSQL.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Whats Missing in the Postgres Docs</h3>

<p>Theres a huge variety of types of documentation, off the top of my head theres:</p>

<ul>
<li>Reference docs (Postgres excels at this)</li>
<li>Onboarding (Postgres tutorial huh?)</li>
<li>Tailored guides (Postgres? I can haz? Nope&hellip; We don&rsquo;t understand&hellip;.)</li>
</ul>


<p>Postgres is great if you know the name of what you&rsquo;re looking for, but if you don&rsquo;t you&rsquo;re entirely left in the dark.</p>

<h3>Understanding the power of Postgres</h3>

<p>Postgres is good enough at performance, good enough at usability, and awesome at how powerful and flexible it can be. But all of this is entirely lost if you have to know the esoteric name of what you&rsquo;re looking for.</p>

<p><em>What the hell is an hstore&hellip; In so many ways KVstore makes infintely more sense. In the same sense PLV8, I have to know not only what PL stands for but V8 as well, versus the JavaScript extension for Postgres.</em></p>

<p>I understand there are plenty of reasons why some of these things are the way they are, but its also limiting how great the broader perception is. Postgres externally is this hard to use DB, that well is just a database, versus giving developers a set of powerful and useful functions to make their lives better.</p>

<h3>The Solution</h3>

<p>Lets fix things, there are a ton of people that would love to know more about all things Postgres. This ranges from a good set of onboarding docs, to specific blog posts on topics that people are curious about. Just last week I got an email about improving <strong>the</strong> Postgres tutorial&hellip; Yes theres a tutorial hidden in the <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.2/static/tutorial.html">2000 page set of documentation for Postgres</a>. Its simply old, mostly uninteresting, and well just needs to be completely recreated. A great alternative would be a few tutorials/guides for:</p>

<ul>
<li>Noobs to databases in general (Total 101 guide)</li>
<li>Building and architecting your application with Postgres (App Devs)</li>
<li>Administering and maintaining Postgres (DBAs)</li>
<li>SQL and reporting in Postgres (consumers of data, analysts, product people, marketing, etc.)</li>
</ul>


<p>If jumping in and contributing to fixing the core tutorial isn&rsquo;t your cup of tea because you don&rsquo;t want to learn and write in <a href="http://www-sul.stanford.edu/tools/tutorials/html2.0/gentle.html">SGML</a>, send a pull request to <a href="http://postgresguide.com">postgresguide.com</a> or do a <a href="mailto:craig.kerstiens@gmail.com].%20If%20thats%20too%20much%20effort%20please%20just%20let%20us%20know,%20what%20do%20you%20want%20to%20see%20-%20[craig.kerstiens%20at%20gmail.com](mailto:craig.kerstiens@gmail.com">guest post on my blog</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A look at Foreign Data Wrappers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/08/05/a-look-at-FDWs/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/08/05/a-look-at-FDWs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are two particular sets of features that continue to keep me very excited about the momentum of Postgres. And while PostgreSQL has had some great momentum in the past few years these features may give it an entirely new pace all together. One is extensions, which is really its own category. Dimitri Fontaine was talking about doing a full series just on extensions, so here&rsquo;s hoping he does so I dont have to :)</p>

<p>One subset of extensions which I consider entirely separate is the other thing, which is foreign data wrappers or FDWs. FDWs allow you to connect to other data sources from within Postgres. From there you can query them with SQL, join across disparate data sets, or join across different systems. Recently I had a good excuse to give the <code>postgres_fdw</code> a try. And while I&rsquo;ve blogged about the Redis FDW previously, the Postgres one is particularly exciting because with PostgreSQL 9.3 it will ship as a contrib module, which means all Postgres installers should have it&hellip; you just have to turn it on.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Let&rsquo;s take a look at getting it setup and then dig into it a bit. First, because I don&rsquo;t have Postgres 9.3 sitting around on my system I&rsquo;m going to provision one from Heroku Postgres:</p>

<pre><code>$ heroku addons:add heroku-postgresql:crane --version 9.3
</code></pre>

<p>Once it becomes available I&rsquo;m going to connect to it then enable the extension:</p>

<pre><code>$ heroku pg:psql BLACK -acraig
# CREATE EXTENSION postgres_fdw;
</code></pre>

<p>Now its there, so we can actually start using it. To use the FDW there&rsquo;s four basic things you&rsquo;ll want to do:</p>

<ol>
<li>Create the remote server</li>
<li>Create a user mapping for the remote server</li>
<li>Create your foreign tables</li>
<li>Start querying some things</li>
</ol>


<h3>The setup</h3>

<p>You&rsquo;ll only need to do each of the following once, once you&rsquo;re server, user and foreign table are all setup you can simply query away. This is a nice advantage over db_link which only exists for the set session. <em>One downside I did find was that you can&rsquo;t use a full Postgres connection string, which would make setting it up much simpler</em>. So onto setting up our server:</p>

<pre><code># CREATE SERVER app_db 
  FOREIGN DATA WRAPPER postgres_fdw 
  OPTIONS (dbname 'dbnamehere', host 'hostname-here);
</code></pre>

<p>Next we&rsquo;ll actually create our user mapping. In this case we&rsquo;ll take the remote username and password and map it to our current user we&rsquo;re already connected with.</p>

<pre><code># CREATE USER MAPPING for user_current 
  SERVER app_db 
  OPTIONS (user 'remote_user', password 'remote_password');
</code></pre>

<p>And finally we&rsquo;re going to configure our tables. <em>There were some additional pains here as there wasn&rsquo;t a perfectly clean way to generate the <code>CREATE TABLE</code>. Sure you could pg_dump just that table, but overall it felt a bit cludgey.</em></p>

<pre><code># CREATE FOREIGN TABLE users
  (
    id integer,
    email text,
      created_at timestamp,
      first_name text,
      last_name text
  )
  SERVER app_db OPTIONS (table_name 'users')
</code></pre>

<p>Now we&rsquo;ve got all of our local data, as well as remote data. For that report against two databases where you previously wrote a ruby or python script, ran a query, constructed another query, then executed it you can directly do in your database. We can simply query our new table &ndash; <code>SELECT * FROM users LIMIT 5;</code></p>

<p>But the real power of foreign data wrappers goes well beyond just Postgres to Postgres. Having a defined contract in translating from one system to another, will really allow reinventing the way we work with data. This is especially true in large datasets where doing ETL on terrabytes of data takes longer than asking the questions of it.</p>

<p>While we&rsquo;re waiting for more FDWs to be ready to use in production situations the Postgres FDW is a great start, <em>though the Redis one is on its way</em>. Even better is that it ships with standard installs of Postgres, meaning it will see more usage and help push them to advance further.</p>

<p><em>One final nicety, you&rsquo;re not required to have ALL Postgres 9.3 DBs, just one that can then connect to the others, so go ahead and give it try :)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Postgres Dollar Quoting]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/08/02/use-dollar-quoting-anywhere/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/08/02/use-dollar-quoting-anywhere</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After my most recent post on <a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2013/07/29/documenting-your-postgres-database/">documenting your database</a> I had a colleague and friend chime in:</p>

<blockquote><p>@craigkerstiens You may want to mention for another post the generality of dollar quoting: it&#8217;s not just for CREATE FUNCTION.</p><footer><strong>@danfarina</strong> <cite><a href='https://twitter.com/danfarina/status/362007008079126528'>twitter.com/danfarina/status/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote>


<p>Luckily I was able to convince him to create the post. You can read a bit more on him below, but without further adieu here&rsquo;s a bit on dollar quoting within Postgres:</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Postgres supports two forms of entry of data literals into the system.
One is the familiar single-quote:</p>

<pre><code>=&gt; SELECT 'hello';
 ?column?
----------
 hello
(1 row)
</code></pre>

<p>This format is problematic when one might be using single quotes in
the textual string.</p>

<p>Postgres also supports another way to enter data
literals, most often seen in <code>CREATE FUNCTION</code>, but can be profitably
used anywhere.  This is called &ldquo;dollar quoting,&rdquo; and it looks like
this:</p>

<pre><code>=&gt; SELECT $$hello's the name of the game$$;
           ?column?
------------------------------
 hello's the name of the game
(1 row)
</code></pre>

<p>If one needs nested dollar quoting, one can specify a string, much
like the &lsquo;heredoc&rsquo; feature seen in some programming languages:</p>

<pre><code>=&gt; SELECT $goodbye$hello's the name of the $$ game$goodbye$;
            ?column?
---------------------------------
 hello's the name of the $$ game
(1 row)
</code></pre>

<p>This can appear anywhere where single quotes would otherwise be,
simplifying tasks like using contractions in database object comments,
for example:</p>

<pre><code>=&gt; CREATE TABLE described(a int);
=&gt; COMMENT ON TABLE described IS $$I'm describing this,
including newlines and an apostrophe in the contraction "I'm."$$;
</code></pre>

<p>Or, alternatively, entry of literals for types that may include
apostrophes in their serialization, such as &lsquo;text&rsquo; or &lsquo;json&rsquo;:</p>

<pre><code>=&gt; CREATE TABLE json(data json);
=&gt; INSERT INTO json(data) VALUES
       ($${"quotation": "'there is no time like the present'"}$$);
</code></pre>

<h3>Security</h3>

<p>Even though dollar quotes can be used to reduce the pain of many
quoting problems, don&rsquo;t be tempted to use them to avoid SQL injection:
an adversary that knows one is using dollar quoting can still mount
exactly the same kind of attacks as if one were using single quotes.</p>

<p>There is also no need, because any place a data literal can appear can
also be used with parameter binding (e.g. <code>$1</code>, <code>$2</code>, <code>$3</code>&hellip;), which one&rsquo;s
Postgres driver should support.  Nevertheless, for data or scripts one
is working with by hand, dollar quoting can make things much easier to
read.</p>

<h3>About the Author</h3>

<p>Daniel Farina is a long time colleague and friend, having worked together at 5 different companies. He&rsquo;s part of the <a href="https://twitter.com/danfarina/status/362007008079126528">Heroku Postgres</a> team as the resident tuple groomer, and the creator of <a href="https://github.com/wal-e/wal-e">WAL-E</a>.</p>

<p><em>As is always the case if you have articles you&rsquo;d like to see created or if you&rsquo;re interested in doing a guest post  please feel free to drop me a line <a href="mailto:craig.kerstiens@gmail.com">craig.kerstiens at gmail.com</a>. And if you have articles you feel are helpful to others in the Postgres world drop me a note as well for including them in <a href="http://www.postgresweekly.com">Postgres Weekly</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
