<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Analytics | Craig Kerstiens]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/categories/analytics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-13T07:49:12-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Craig Kerstiens]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[craig.kerstiens@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Attribution 101]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/03/18/attribution-101/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/03/18/attribution-101</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing with the recent posts on metrics and marketing. I want to give a quick primer on attribution. To any marketing or analytics people out there, simply skip this it would aim to be a primer recap at best for you.</p>

<p>The very general meaning behind attribution is to give credit. When it comes to web products this can be giving credit for lots of things:</p>

<ul>
    <li>A visit to your site</li>
    <li>A purchase to your site</li>
    <li>Other events, such as sign up, referring friends, etc.</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p>Its really wonderful when there&rsquo;s a direct mapping in correlation. Take for example the case where:</p>

<ol>
    <li>User sees your ad on facebook</li>
    <li>User clicks on ad</li>
    <li>User signs up for an account</li>
    <li>User pays you money</li>
</ol>


<p>In this case it&rsquo;s clear that its worthwhile to advertise on facebook. The hard part becomes when there&rsquo;s a non-linear path in some form (which is almost always the case). Now take the case:</p>

<ol>
    <li>User sees your ad on facebook</li>
    <li>User clicks on ad, then leaves</li>
    <li>User comes back a day later directly, and spends 10 minutes on the site reading</li>
    <li>User comes back a day later after searching via google, and creates an account</li>
    <li>User sees a re targeting ad 1 month later and visits</li>
    <li>User pays for account</li>
</ol>


<p>In a perfect world you have case 1 and can give the full credit or attribution of the purchase to your facebook ad. However, in a real world you have case 2 and it becomes more complicated. Perhaps its something like this though:</p>

<ul>
    <li>Account creation - 100% to facebook ad</li>
    <li>Paying for account - 50% to facebook ad, 50% to retargetting?</li>
</ul>


<p>This is where there is not an exact science to attribution, as it could be justified to give 100% of the credit for paying for an account to the re targeting. So if this has you pondering on attribution here&rsquo;s the downer part&hellip;. The tools that allow you to attribute a goal or action to multiple sources:</p>

<ul>
    <li>Omniture</li>
    <li>Web Trends</li>
</ul>


<p>Most other tools are the last place the user ever came from, some occasionally are the first place a user came from, but without pony-ing up for a high end product your options on actually getting data don&rsquo;t really exist.</p>

<p>&nbsp;</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: I have little to no formal training in stats or analytics, have simply learned through launching products so take this for what its worth, someone that has been there and done it.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reading Metrics to Evaluate Marketing]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/03/02/understanding-metrics/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/03/02/understanding-metrics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A short while backed I talked about <a href="http://www.craigekerstiens.com/2011/02/03/tactical-steps-for-startup-metrics/">tactically measuring metrics</a> for your site/company. Recently I talked a bit about <a href="http://www.craigekerstiens.com/2011/02/14/bootstrappedstartup-marketing-part-1/">methods of marketing</a>. A large key to getting the most out of your time and money is to properly report against the intersection of these two items. First I&rsquo;m going to make the assumption you&rsquo;ve read those posts, if you haven&rsquo;t go back and do that. Next this is heavily on the assumption that you&rsquo;re using Google Analytics as your primary tool for measuring metrics and have setup goals appropriately.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Within measuring you&rsquo;re metrics you&rsquo;ll have abandonment at each level. You may have some visitors that never register, and many that register but never purchase anything. It&rsquo;s wonderful if you&rsquo;re able to immediately have full insight of the best means of marketing to drive revenue, however realistically it occurs in a more phased approach. The first step is to drive visitors and almost immediate second is to convert those users as registered.</p>

<p><em><strong>Acquisition &ndash;&gt; Activation</strong></em></p>

<p>This at a high level makes sense, as does at a high level knowing you should be targeting users in your target market. However, even slightly drilling into this you realize that all traffic is not equal. It&rsquo;s often known that CPC and CPA advertising does not convert well for users, though can drive traffic. This may not always be the case. For Registry Stop to make this analysis easier we&rsquo;ve created a custom report in google.</p>

<p>To create your own custom report simply click Manage Custom Reports under the Custom Reports area then &ldquo;Create new custom report&rdquo;. The custom report ability in google gives you much more ability to drill into the data that you already have at a higher level. To track effectiveness of converting visitors to registered users and which sources are effective at this you&rsquo;d create something that looks like:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz024.png"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-366" title="Creating Custom Report" src="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz024-300x205.png" alt="Creating Custom Report" width="300" height="205" /></a></p>

<p>Here while very simple we&rsquo;re able to see some very key information quickly. Here&rsquo;s an example of how it would appear over a few day period:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz0231.png"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-368" title="Google Analytics - Goals Custom Report" src="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz0231-300x205.png" alt="Google Analytics - Goals Custom Report" width="300" height="205" /></a></p>

<p>&nbsp;</p>

<p>As you progress in your stage of bootstrapping or growing your startup you&rsquo;ll want to grow custom reports that allow you to report against as many <a href="http://www.craigekerstiens.com/2011/02/03/tactical-steps-for-startup-metrics/">metrics</a> as possible. The first and last part of my day is spent pouring over these reports. Having this data readily available allows us to drive our business based on data. Perhaps the hardest part of all of this is admitting when the data is counter to what we expect and following its advice.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up Goals and Funnels - Google Analytics]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/02/28/setting-goals-funnels/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-28T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/02/28/setting-goals-funnels</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had a recent request on how to setup a funnel in Google Analytics. If you&rsquo;ve missed by first post on some tips for <a href="http://www.craigekerstiens.com/2011/02/02/events-with-google-analytics-and-tricking-pageviews/">Google Analytics</a> first check that out. With most websites today there is some portion of the site that is event and not page based, meaning you have some workflow on the page based on Javascript. If this is the case you&rsquo;ll want to <a href="http://www.craigekerstiens.com/2011/02/02/events-with-google-analytics-and-tricking-pageviews/">fake a page view</a> instead of an event in order to entirely use it in funnels and goals.</p>

<p>A personal recommendation is actually to use both, goals and funnels. The key a funnel is that you need to have successive steps that occur in some order. With regards to metrics tracking this is absolutely needed, but typically you may have 1-2 total funnels with many steps in your site versus goals where you could have 10-15 single goals. For <a href="http://www.registrystop.com">Registry Stop</a> we&rsquo;ve structured our site so that our earlier stage goals become the same as steps in later stage funnels. For us in almost all cases the first part of the funnel is the visit, the second is registering for an account. We do have independent goals for visits and registrations as well, but we do not have funnels on those goals.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>A key to getting the most use out of your funnels is to know that there is a <strong>workflow to follow</strong> to getting to that end goal. To highlight this slightly more visually let me walk through an example:</p>

<ol>
    <li><em><strong>User visits your site.</strong></em></li>
Here you'll want to create a goal. Likely this is tracking a page view of the homepage.
    <li><em><strong>User registers for an account.</strong></em></li>
Here again, you'll create a goal and nothing more. If there is a confirmation page that will be your goal, if there is not, then you'll want to <a href="http://www.craigekerstiens.com/2011/02/02/events-with-google-analytics-and-tricking-pageviews/">fake a page view</a> in order to track that goal.
    <li><em><strong>User adds a product</strong></em></li>
This is the first place you want to create both a goal and a funnel.</ol>


<p>With regards to the goal, it should be pretty simple, tracking some page view. For the funnel though you will likely have 4 parts.</p>

<p>The parts of your funnel will be:</p>

<ol>
    <li>User visits your site.</li>
    <li>User registers for an account.</li>
    <li>User begins process of adding a product</li>
    <li>User completes product add</li>
</ol>


<p>For Registry Stop we have a similar funnel for users which includes:</p>

<ol>
    <li>Registering for an account</li>
    <li>Visiting the sync page</li>
    <li>Adding a synced registry</li>
</ol>


<p>Now as for actually setting up a goal or funnel. This is slightly unintuitive as it&rsquo;s not from inside a specific site on Google Analytics. At the home level of google analytics you&rsquo;ll have all of your sites setup. For each site to the right you&rsquo;ll have actions, click the Edit to go to the goal area.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz011.png"><img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-348" title="Google Analytics Settings - Goals and Funnels" src="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz011.png" alt="Google Analytics Settings - Goals and Funnels" width="125" height="64" /></a></p>

<p>Once here it becomes a bit more intuitive. You can begin by simply adding a goal. Your goal types should seem mostly intuitive, as mentioned in an earlier post you cannot use an Event in a goal. For this reason you can fake a pageview as if it actually occurred and then create your goal against that non-existent page view. If you want a few more details of how to do this check out the previous post . So for an example, we have a goal on <a href="http://www.registrystop.com">Registry Stop</a> that detects when a page view occurs as a result of a registry being synced. Because this workflow is heavily javascript and flow based we fake the page view and track it as if the page was actually visited. The goal itself looks like:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz012.png"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-350" title="Google Analytics Example Goal" src="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz012.png" alt="Google Analytics Example Goal" width="300" height="75" /></a></p>

<p>For setting up your funnel as we mentioned above its generally a set of page views. A very key item is the check box next to the first item in your funnel. If you check this is means any other steps in the funnel are not counted unless you the first step is completed. If you have a very structured 1, 2, 3 workflow this makes sense. However, if there are various ways for the goal to complete then be very careful about selecting this.</p>

<p>For this same goal above we have a corresponding funnel to track in detail how our conversion flows. The funnel itself looks like this once setup:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz022.png"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-344" title="Google Analytics Funnel Setup" src="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz022.png" alt="Google Analytics Funnel Setup" width="300" height="127" /></a></p>

<p>This results in a funnel report that looks like:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz011.png"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-342" title="Synced Registry Funnel" src="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz011.png" alt="Synced Registry Funnel" width="300" height="250" /></a></p>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tactical Steps for Startup Metrics]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/02/03/tactical-steps-for-startup-metrics/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-03T19:39:54-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/02/03/tactical-steps-for-startup-metrics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Metrics are obviously a very valuable area for start-ups, if you don&rsquo;t believe in metrics and think you&rsquo;re idea wins just because its great then you better start searching for your next day job. <a href="http://twitter.com/davemcclure">Dave McClure</a> has done a great talk on start-ups several times over, you can check out a video and corresponding slide show at:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.ustream.tv/recorded/5336115"><a href="http://www.ustream.tv/recorded/5336115">http://www.ustream.tv/recorded/5336115</a></a>
<a href="http://www.slideshare.net/dmc500hats/startup-metrics-for-pirates-long-version"><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/dmc500hats/startup-metrics-for-pirates-long-version">http://www.slideshare.net/dmc500hats/startup-metrics-for-pirates-long-version</a></a></p>

<p>And besides, it&rsquo;s a pirates acronym, so it&rsquo;s got to be great. But translating these from concept to actual technology metrics is also something that needs discussion. You can&rsquo;t exactly say we&rsquo;re going to use Google Analytics and let it magically tell you everything, furthermore all of the web developers out there talking about tweaks on Google Analytics do little to actually tell you what you need to know.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>To start with I&rsquo;m going to lay out a few of the key features of Google Analytics, assuming it&rsquo;s the key backbone for web analytics, and because it really is an amazing free tool.If you&rsquo;re not familiar with google analytics go and explore before reading this, we&rsquo;re going to skip right over the basics of what are visitors and traffic sources directly to what you need to use and customise to get valuable metrics for a start-up. Diving right in a few key items:</p>

<p>Goals &ndash; These are custom items that you want to setup. What is a goal? Well that can be a bit abstract but it can be a specific page that was visited, time spent on the site, or a certain number of pages per visit.</p>

<p>Events &ndash; Here you can start track events to any type of your liking. In most cases this can be some in page action, but the key here is to each event you can track a value. This starts to become useful if you want to track most shared content, most liked products, or other items. Typically those kinds of items might exist within your in-house database, but exposing it to Google Analytics gives you an extra level of reporting integration</p>

<p>Custom Reporting &ndash; Google is great out of the box, if you feel like it just grazes the surface then you haven&rsquo;t explored it. But in some cases it&rsquo;s easier to create a custom report of data that you can&rsquo;t get exactly to, or to get very quick insight into similar data.</p>

<p>So this is a really high level, but how do you use each of the above to tie to actually implementing the metrics you care about? We&rsquo;ll go through an example of how you track each of Dave McClure&rsquo;s 5 key metrics based. For those of you not familiar with his metrics, please go to the above links and listen to his presentation first.</p>

<ol>
    <li>Acquisition, this one is pretty obvious. Google does this out of the box for you. The key reports you're likely to care about here are Visitors and Traffic Sources. You care about how many overall users you get and where they are coming from. If you're spending money on blog posts and its not getting visitors then give up on it. If you've barely focused on SEO, but are already getting organic traffic from google, well then WORK on SEO. One key thing you'll start to look into is when people bounce. Do they come from CPC ads and have an 90% bounce rate, if so they may click on the ad, but once they get to your site something turns them off. You're goal is to get users, and get them to explore the site.</li>
    <li>Activation, this one can start to vary pretty heavily. In this case lets assume you want a user to sign up for some form of free account. In some cases activation may be viewing a certain number of pages or certain set of pages, but often times capturing some information that you can track back to a user is key. This could be via facebook connect, a signup with email, or twitter. Regardless of what you consider an activation, likely one of the easiest ways to track this is with some form of a goal. If you have a fully javascript based process, more power to you, but it makes a specific page view a bit harder, but only slightly. Check our post on <a href="http://www.craigekerstiens.com/events-with-google-analytics-and-tricking-pageviews/">how to simulate a page view</a> along with how to track an event in google analytics. In this case you're goal might only be one step, in the case that several steps are required look into creating a funnel.</li>
1 and 2 are generally straightforward. You get a user to the sight and you get one to sign up. So what? Well keep going....
    <li>Retention, you need a user to come back. If you're going to make money someone has to keep coming back, unless you're damn good at sales, you're not going to sell them a penny on the first visit for $100. You need them to establish some brand recognition and continue to come back to you. Sure google will easily tell you how many are new visitors and how many are return, but this is only minimally helpful. What's bringing back return users, is it your blog posts, twitter, email campaigns. The best way to track what's keeping your users coming back is likely a custom report. This way you can check your traffic sources, along with which users are return visitors. What you likely want to drill down into from the first level is which content your users are visiting. Is what you feel a key feature not being used from a certain source? Is it an issue of marketing or not a valuable feature? Dave McClure has a recent idea of kill it, and see if users yell, this is definitely one way to tell if its useful. It's probably easiest to create a report to start with and see what's the usage of pages/content.</li>
    <li>Referral, very possibly this is the hardest to track. In our case we track it in several forms. First is that someone is sharing something, this could be via twitter/fb/email. Since most sites are building some form of social sharing directly into their applications. It can be a bit hard to tell which part of a referral users engage and abandon in. We recommend a couple of options here, the first is tracking events. Events truly exist for just this purpose, tracking various events. In this case you might track events based on a category of referral, and separate events being:
<ul>
    <li>Email</li>
    <li>Twitter</li>
    <li>FB</li>
</ul>
With values being
<ul>
    <li>Shared</li>
    <li>Abandoned</li>
</ul>
</li>
Overall you can have a good bit of flexibility with events, but the hard part is reporting against them. If you want numeric values tracked events are the way to go, but if its a straight forward process, then you may want to simulate a page view at each step. The reason for this is that you could then great a goal, which has a full funnel to it. Funnels are very helpful at being able to visualise how many users proceed to the next step in a goal. In our example of visiting a page, selecting a method to share, authenticating, and sharing, its clear that every step must be taken. If you can structure your goals this way by all means create a funnel. If not, simple goal or event tracking can suffice.
    <li>Revenue, of course it comes down to money in the bank at the end of the day. Here events are almost inevitable, especially if you can tie an exact amount to your revenue. If however there's a set amount of revenue based on either the ads or based on the type of account a user registers for. If you have the ability to make this a page view then go for it, such as by 3 account levels. In most cases though what you'll care about it is the exact revenue you can make, if you can't tied this to a category or account level, tie it directly to the event. Events, as mentioned above, let you tie an exact value to the event. Of course you could easily compute revenue from your in house reporting system, but the ability to tie revenue to other metrics/dimensions is where you get your real value.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
