<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Startup | Craig Kerstiens]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/categories/startup/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-12T09:37:17-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Craig Kerstiens]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[craig.kerstiens@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Going from blog posts to full launches]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2015/12/26/from-blog-posts-to-launches/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2015/12/26/from-blog-posts-to-launches</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recall extremely early stage where you&rsquo;d build a feature, realize it was awesome, then the next day write a blog post for it. At some point you start to move from that to more coordinated launches. A larger coordinated launch allows you to reach a bigger audience, can lead to bigger deals, and help expand your overall market. But perhaps more importantly by the time you hit full launch you&rsquo;ve message tested and ensured it&rsquo;s going to resonate in the way you expect.</p>

<p><em>The process itself will both help amplify and validate/refine your message</em></p>

<p>This is often a more gradual process than a sudden single change, you&rsquo;ll introduce new parts of this in time. And for many what an entire launch process looks like comes by trial an error, to help shorten that learning curve here&rsquo;s key areas I pay attention for a launch and process followed by a rough timeline.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Product first</h3>

<p>Making sure the product is in the right shape is key to any big launch. You don&rsquo;t get a second shot and if the product isn&rsquo;t in shape customers often won&rsquo;t take a second look at it later. For this reason I strongly prefer to have your product locked and loaded before you even start talking launch times, or at least be in the bug clean up phase. This means you&rsquo;ve built a feature, validated with alpha users or private beta, and are ready to open it up to the world.</p>

<p>If you have to set a launch date without the product or feature being already done allow padding. Sometimes it&rsquo;s good for the team to know the padding, sometimes it isn&rsquo;t. When you have extra time it&rsquo;s not uncommon for your development to magically consume exactly that amount of time and still result in a small scramble towards the end.</p>

<p>A good driver I&rsquo;ve found is needing to have it fully like to demo a few weeks out from the launch itself, such as during <a href="">analyst pre-briefings</a>.</p>

<h3>Crafting your message</h3>

<p>Every launch is an opportunity to tell your core message and value prop. If you miss this opportunity for focusing on a single narrow feature you&rsquo;ve missed the biggest opportunity you had in a launch. You can&rsquo;t relaunch your full product every time though–you do need some big improvements or feature that you can highlight, but you should still hit your core message.</p>

<p>First you should know that your feature solves some specific problem, you should know this from the alpha/beta testing and if it doesn&rsquo;t solve this problem <a href="/2014/08/13/when-to-ship-when-to-kill/">you&rsquo;re not ready to launch</a>. Yes, some people will launch a product before the product is completely there–this is common in a marketing driven company as opposed to a product/engineering driven company.</p>

<p>Your message should lead with the problem you&rsquo;re solving, not the laundry list of features. The best launches lead with some  broader thematic message, even better if it&rsquo;s an altruistic world changing one. A rough example of this:</p>

<p>To the point to the product, and probably over generalized as boring:</p>

<ul>
<li>Connectify brings a new way of taking your dumb devices at home and turning them into intelligent connected devices.</li>
</ul>


<p>In contrast, broad thematic message, followed lightly by the product.</p>

<ul>
<li>We live in a connected world, and with new connected devices there&rsquo;s the opportunity not just give you more data but help you improve how you live your life. Connectify helps you at bringing the devices that matter together with ease.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Testing your message</h3>

<p>You should treat your message just like a product, testing it gradually along the way. Once you&rsquo;ve got some initial framing of it, test it internally, then with friendly customers or community members. Leading up to the launch I usually have a timeline and get all the content and communication rolling about 3 weeks out. I&rsquo;ll give a bit of a timeline below but first some more around message testing</p>

<h4>Analysts</h4>

<p>If you regularly use <a href="/2015/07/25/A-guide-to-analyst-relations-for-startups/">any analysts</a> you should absolutely use them to help with a launch. Several weeks out is a great time to test key messages with them, get feedback, and if you&rsquo;re lucky you may even get them to provide a quote for the launch.</p>

<p>Keep in mind here a inquiry is an opportunity to test your message and get feedback. You should talk roughly half of the time here, they should be talking the other half. In contrast briefings before launch you should have your message fully baked and should simply be pitching your message and possibly demo-ing.</p>

<h4>Friendlies</h4>

<p>This may be more contentious, but at least at early stage sharing drafts with friendly community members is a great way to get feedback and refine your message. Here you should be especially concious of the request of their time and expect to have some delay before they get back to you. Being top secret about your message ahead of time won&rsquo;t add much value to it being a home run, where as better ensuring it resonates will help it to be more successful.</p>

<h4>Customers</h4>

<p>Customers I call out as a separate bucket. Customers have less incentive to leak your news than friendlies, but also fall somewhere on the other spectrum of analysts. A key piece about customers is there is an opportunity for them to be a launch partner. And so on to that topic:</p>

<h3>Launch partners</h3>

<p>Press and others like seeing and knowing you have external validation. Similarly many see the benefit of being part of a launch, after all it&rsquo;s more free press for them. For a launch partner there are various levels, though for most providing some quote is a pretty common level.</p>

<p>The best way to do this is talk to them about what they like about the feature/product and take a first stab at the quote for them from their feedback. Some may very much want to wordsmith their own which is fine, but minimizing the work required of them while–trying to hit something they&rsquo;d say as well–as a message that flows can best be done by you taking a first pass.</p>

<p>Further there&rsquo;s varying levels of value with quotes and references. In descending order:</p>

<ol>
<li>Customers</li>
<li>Analysts</li>
<li>Community Members</li>
</ol>


<h3>The other details</h3>

<p>During launch week I mostly want to be dotting i&rsquo;s and crossing t&rsquo;s, meaning: I want the product done. I want documentation done. I want the blog post finalized. I want to be in the mode of send internal announcements, prep internal teams, talk to media.</p>

<h4>Prepping internal teams</h4>

<p>Obviously the engineering and product people involved will be in the loop. But you need to notify many others some of which should have been in the loop already, some less so:</p>

<ul>
<li>Support &ndash; There&rsquo;s a new product surface area, support should be top of your list so they can field the tickets and questions that come in</li>
<li>Sales &ndash; Even if there is no price change or impact, new features allow sales to communicate value to customers</li>
</ul>


<h3>Timeline</h3>

<p>Finally what&rsquo;s the end to end timeline look like with all the little details. Here&rsquo;s a rough one that&rsquo;s fully built out. IF you&rsquo;re smaller and don&rsquo;t have a regular cadence of analysts in hand then just expect that doesn&rsquo;t apply. IF your support team is the product and engineers maybe that&rsquo;s lighter weight. Basically feel free to take out parts, but expect your process to grow to something of this size.</p>

<ul>
<li>4 weeks out &ndash; Outline of blog post with key messages</li>
<li>Test that outline internally</li>
<li>3 weeks out &ndash; Start to get a rough draft in place</li>
<li>3 weeks out &ndash; Share internally and with friendlies. At this point you&rsquo;re explicitely looking for message feedback. Tell people to not waste time on nitpicks of words or grammar, it will be 98% re-written by the time you&rsquo;re done</li>
<li>2.5 weeks out &ndash; Analyst inquiries for message testing</li>
<li>2.5 weeks out &ndash; Start putting together product demo</li>
<li>2 weeks out &ndash; Start putting together documentation</li>
<li>2 weeks out &ndash; Start nailing down blog post for final messages</li>
<li>1 weeks out &ndash; Start to put final touches on blog post for grammar</li>
<li>1 week out &ndash; Analyst briefings</li>
<li>1 week out &ndash; Update support</li>
<li>3-5 days out &ndash; Stage blog post</li>
<li>3-5 days out &ndash; Stage new documentation</li>
<li>2-4 days out &ndash; Make sure PRs are ready or feature flags, in short the switch is there or live but not public</li>
<li>1-3 days out &ndash; Update sales</li>
<li>1-3 days out &ndash; Interall communication to all@</li>
<li>1-3 days out &ndash; Media briefings</li>
<li>LAUNCH DAY &ndash; Sit in a room and watch all the things, engage with twitter/HN/etc.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Securing your Internal Organization with OpenID]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2012/01/23/securing-your-organization/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-23T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2012/01/23/securing-your-organization</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve recently been amazed at the number of companies that are still using a VPN or other means to manage their apps/network. Not just large enterprisey companies, but small agile startups. I fully understand that it works, but 95% of these places are also using another key tool for access inside their company&hellip; <em>Google Apps</em>. I fully expect companies to use google apps, its more of the former that surprises me most. For a long time OpenID wasn&rsquo;t at a usable point, even today it still isn&rsquo;t without its faults. However, it does make for a much cleaner workflow once in place than having your users login to something with they&rsquo;re used to using elsewhere.</p>

<p>In our personal lives we use email as our keys to the kingdom. In fact I now almost refuse to sign up for any service that doesn&rsquo;t let me use oauth, so why should a work place be much different. So I inquired with a few companies to see if they were fine with securing things like documentation or wiki&rsquo;s being google auth, they indeed were. Yet they still seem to have users keep one more username and password for their VPN to be able to login to access internal docs/tools.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Most tech centric companies grow their own apps for many things they do within a company. Even the heavier adopters of SaaS still end up building a lot of internal systems. So why not secure them with your email domain just as you commonly would if it were a public service?</p>

<p>The problem comes in that OpenId with google has an initial setup overhead, but after that works unbelievably well.</p>

<h2>The catch</h2>

<p>In some cases you currently have to identify your domain as an OpenId provider. This means that @yourname.com is an OpenId provider. This simply means creating a url route for openid in your base site similar to the below:</p>

<p>``` xml <a href="http://heroku.com/openid">http://heroku.com/openid</a>
&lt;?xml version=&ldquo;1.0&rdquo; encoding=&ldquo;UTF-8&rdquo;?>
&lt;xrds:XRDS xmlns:xrds=&ldquo;xri://$xrds&rdquo; xmlns=&ldquo;xri://$xrd<em>($v</em>2.0)&rdquo;>
  <XRD></p>

<pre><code>&lt;Service priority="0"&gt;
  &lt;Type&gt;http://specs.openid.net/auth/2.0/signon&lt;/Type&gt;
  &lt;URI&gt;https://www.google.com/a/craigkerstiens.com/o8/ud?be=o8&lt;/URI&gt;
&lt;/Service&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>  </XRD>
&lt;/xrds:XRDS>
```</p>

<p><em>This is due to an issue of OpenID discovery which you can read more on at: <a href="https://groups.google.com/group/google-federated-login-api/browse_thread/thread/4a7dd2312a47a082/9285cec18a30b9d3?lnk=gst&amp;q=apps+discovery&amp;pli=1#9285cec18a30b9d3.">https://groups.google.com/group/google-federated-login-api/browse_thread/thread/4a7dd2312a47a082/9285cec18a30b9d3?lnk=gst&amp;q=apps+discovery&amp;pli=1#9285cec18a30b9d3.</a> In short, setting up the above can save you a lot of time</em></p>

<h2>Setting up in apps</h2>

<p>Most web frameworks have libraries that make it easy to secure your apps with openid/oauth. In particular Django and Rails both make this pretty easy. To make this even simpler for you below is code to actually secure an internal app for both Django and Rails. You can do similar with Flask or Sinatra as well.</p>

<h3>Rails</h3>

<p>In case your admin controller isn&rsquo;t already generated:</p>

<p><code>
rails g controller admin/users
</code></p>

<p>Then anything you want to secure:</p>

<p>```
module Admin
  class UsersController &lt; ApplicationController</p>

<pre><code>before_filter :admin_required

def index
  render :text =&gt; 'Hello from the admin panel!'
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<h3>Django</h3>

<p>Finally sync your database:</p>

<p><code>
python yourapp/manage.py syncdb
</code></p>

<p>Secure any view with the <code>login_required</code> decorator as your typically would with Django.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>In short with some very basic app setup you can have an internal workflow thats just as good as what you use in your day to day outside the office.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Attribution 101]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/03/18/attribution-101/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/03/18/attribution-101</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing with the recent posts on metrics and marketing. I want to give a quick primer on attribution. To any marketing or analytics people out there, simply skip this it would aim to be a primer recap at best for you.</p>

<p>The very general meaning behind attribution is to give credit. When it comes to web products this can be giving credit for lots of things:</p>

<ul>
    <li>A visit to your site</li>
    <li>A purchase to your site</li>
    <li>Other events, such as sign up, referring friends, etc.</li>
</ul>


<!--more-->


<p>Its really wonderful when there&rsquo;s a direct mapping in correlation. Take for example the case where:</p>

<ol>
    <li>User sees your ad on facebook</li>
    <li>User clicks on ad</li>
    <li>User signs up for an account</li>
    <li>User pays you money</li>
</ol>


<p>In this case it&rsquo;s clear that its worthwhile to advertise on facebook. The hard part becomes when there&rsquo;s a non-linear path in some form (which is almost always the case). Now take the case:</p>

<ol>
    <li>User sees your ad on facebook</li>
    <li>User clicks on ad, then leaves</li>
    <li>User comes back a day later directly, and spends 10 minutes on the site reading</li>
    <li>User comes back a day later after searching via google, and creates an account</li>
    <li>User sees a re targeting ad 1 month later and visits</li>
    <li>User pays for account</li>
</ol>


<p>In a perfect world you have case 1 and can give the full credit or attribution of the purchase to your facebook ad. However, in a real world you have case 2 and it becomes more complicated. Perhaps its something like this though:</p>

<ul>
    <li>Account creation - 100% to facebook ad</li>
    <li>Paying for account - 50% to facebook ad, 50% to retargetting?</li>
</ul>


<p>This is where there is not an exact science to attribution, as it could be justified to give 100% of the credit for paying for an account to the re targeting. So if this has you pondering on attribution here&rsquo;s the downer part&hellip;. The tools that allow you to attribute a goal or action to multiple sources:</p>

<ul>
    <li>Omniture</li>
    <li>Web Trends</li>
</ul>


<p>Most other tools are the last place the user ever came from, some occasionally are the first place a user came from, but without pony-ing up for a high end product your options on actually getting data don&rsquo;t really exist.</p>

<p>&nbsp;</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: I have little to no formal training in stats or analytics, have simply learned through launching products so take this for what its worth, someone that has been there and done it.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Startup/Bootstrapped Marketing Recap]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/03/07/startupbootstrapped-marketing-recap/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-07T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/03/07/startupbootstrapped-marketing-recap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you have an hour to spare its well worth it to look back and look back at my series on startup/bootstrapped marketing. But if you&rsquo;re short on time and want the high level summary here&rsquo;s the quick recap:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/02/14/bootstrappedstartup-marketing-part-1/">Part 1 &ndash; Focus on SEO</a></p>

<ul>
    <li>Ensure you have a sitemap; <a href="http://www.google.com/support/webmasters/bin/answer.py?answer=183668">http://www.google.com/support/webmasters/bin/answer.py?answer=183668</a>
<ul>
    <li>Submit it to google</li>
    <li>Submit it to yahoo</li>
    <li>Submit it to bing</li>
</ul>
<!--more-->
</li>
    <li>Use meta tags and ensure they're unique</li>
    <li>Use unique titles and h1/h2 tags in your pages</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/02/16/bootstrappedstartup-marketing-part-2/">Part 2 &ndash; Find Influencers</a></p>

<ul>
    <li>Find the key bloggers</li>
    <li>Be brief and to the point</li>
    <li>Provide value to them, often by an exclusive</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/02/18/bootstrappedstartup-marketing-part-3/">Part 3 &ndash; Traditional Advertising</a></p>

<ul>
    <li>Contextual - AdSense, target for competitors</li>
    <li>Demographic - Cast wide net for demographic info, narrow on interests/hobbies</li>
    <li>Vertical - Ensure to filter out noise and focus on brand</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/02/22/bootstrappedstartup-marketing-part-4/">Part 4 &ndash; Retargetting</a></p>

<ul>
    <li>No matter what do this step, it make's you appear to have a larger presence than you do to users</li>
    <li>Most recommended service: <a href="http://www.adroll.com">AdRoll</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Again this is just a very high level recap. If any of these items strikes a chord with you please dive deeper. The amount of time it takes to learn about how to market and target your users is a fraction of the return you get from doing it effectively. Finally, if anyone out there needs direction on how to target and measure more effectively always feel free to reach out to me, i&rsquo;m easily found on <a href="http://www.twitter.com/craigkerstiens">twitter</a> among many other services.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reading Metrics to Evaluate Marketing]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/03/02/understanding-metrics/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2011/03/02/understanding-metrics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A short while backed I talked about <a href="http://www.craigekerstiens.com/2011/02/03/tactical-steps-for-startup-metrics/">tactically measuring metrics</a> for your site/company. Recently I talked a bit about <a href="http://www.craigekerstiens.com/2011/02/14/bootstrappedstartup-marketing-part-1/">methods of marketing</a>. A large key to getting the most out of your time and money is to properly report against the intersection of these two items. First I&rsquo;m going to make the assumption you&rsquo;ve read those posts, if you haven&rsquo;t go back and do that. Next this is heavily on the assumption that you&rsquo;re using Google Analytics as your primary tool for measuring metrics and have setup goals appropriately.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Within measuring you&rsquo;re metrics you&rsquo;ll have abandonment at each level. You may have some visitors that never register, and many that register but never purchase anything. It&rsquo;s wonderful if you&rsquo;re able to immediately have full insight of the best means of marketing to drive revenue, however realistically it occurs in a more phased approach. The first step is to drive visitors and almost immediate second is to convert those users as registered.</p>

<p><em><strong>Acquisition &ndash;&gt; Activation</strong></em></p>

<p>This at a high level makes sense, as does at a high level knowing you should be targeting users in your target market. However, even slightly drilling into this you realize that all traffic is not equal. It&rsquo;s often known that CPC and CPA advertising does not convert well for users, though can drive traffic. This may not always be the case. For Registry Stop to make this analysis easier we&rsquo;ve created a custom report in google.</p>

<p>To create your own custom report simply click Manage Custom Reports under the Custom Reports area then &ldquo;Create new custom report&rdquo;. The custom report ability in google gives you much more ability to drill into the data that you already have at a higher level. To track effectiveness of converting visitors to registered users and which sources are effective at this you&rsquo;d create something that looks like:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz024.png"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-366" title="Creating Custom Report" src="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz024-300x205.png" alt="Creating Custom Report" width="300" height="205" /></a></p>

<p>Here while very simple we&rsquo;re able to see some very key information quickly. Here&rsquo;s an example of how it would appear over a few day period:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz0231.png"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-368" title="Google Analytics - Goals Custom Report" src="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/images/Snapz-Pro-XScreenSnapz0231-300x205.png" alt="Google Analytics - Goals Custom Report" width="300" height="205" /></a></p>

<p>&nbsp;</p>

<p>As you progress in your stage of bootstrapping or growing your startup you&rsquo;ll want to grow custom reports that allow you to report against as many <a href="http://www.craigekerstiens.com/2011/02/03/tactical-steps-for-startup-metrics/">metrics</a> as possible. The first and last part of my day is spent pouring over these reports. Having this data readily available allows us to drive our business based on data. Perhaps the hardest part of all of this is admitting when the data is counter to what we expect and following its advice.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
