<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Postgres, | Craig Kerstiens]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/categories/postgres/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-09-18T18:18:59-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Craig Kerstiens]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[craig.kerstiens@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tracking and managing your Postgres connections]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2017/09/18/postgres-connection-management/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2017/09/18/postgres-connection-management</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Managing connections in Postgres is a topic that seems to come up several times a week in conversations. I&rsquo;ve written some about scaling your connections and the right approach when you truly need a high level of connections, which is to use a connection pooler like pgBouncer. But what do you do before that point and how can you better track what is going on with your connections in Postgres? <!--more--></p>

<p>Postgres under the covers has a lot of metadata about both historical and current activity against a system. Within Postgres you can run the following query which will give you a few results:</p>

<p>```sql
SELECT count(*),</p>

<pre><code>   state 
</code></pre>

<p>FROM pg_stat_activity
GROUP BY 2;
 count |             state
&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;+&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&ndash;</p>

<pre><code> 7 | active
69 | idle
26 | idle in transaction
11 | idle in transaction (aborted)
</code></pre>

<p>(4 rows)</p>

<p>Time: 30.337 ms
```</p>

<p>Each of these is useful in determining what you should do to better manage your connection count. All of these numbers can be useful to record every say 30 seconds and chart on your own internal monitoring. Lets break down each:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>active</strong> &ndash; This is currently running queries, in a sense this is truly how many connections you may require at a time</li>
<li><strong>idle</strong> &ndash; This is where you have opened a connection to the DB (most frameworks do this and maintain a pool of them), but nothing is happening. This is the one area that a connection pooler like pgBouncer can most help.</li>
<li><strong>idle in transaction</strong> &ndash; This is where your app has run a <code>BEGIN</code> but it&rsquo;s now waiting somewhere in a transaction and not doing work.</li>
</ul>


<p>For <strong>idle</strong> as mentioned above it&rsquo;s one that you do want to monitor and if you see a high number here it&rsquo;s worth investing in setting up a pgBouncer.</p>

<p>For <strong>idle in transaction</strong> this one is a bit more interesting. Here what you likely want to do when first investigating is get an idea of how old those are. You can do this by querying pg_stat_activity and filtering for where the state is <code>idle in transaction</code> and checking how old those queries are. For ones that have been running too long you may want to manually kill them.</p>

<p>If you find that you have some stale transactions hanging around this could be for days, hours, or even just a few minutes you may want to set a default to kill those transactions.</p>

<p>To help with this Postgres has a nice feature of a <code>statement_timeout</code>. A statement timeout will automatically kill queries that run longer than the allotted time. You can set this at both a global level and for a specific session. To do this at the database level you&rsquo;d run this with an <code>alter database dbnamehere set statement_timeout = 60000;</code> which is 60 seconds. To do so during a given session simply run <code>set statment_timeout = 6000000;</code>.</p>

<p>For <em>idle in transaction</em> that have been running too long there is its own setting setting that you can set in a similar fashion <code>idle_in_transaction_session_timeout</code> (on Postgres 9.6 and up). Setting both <code>statement_timeout</code> and <code>idle_in_transaction_session_timeout</code> will help with cancelling long running queries and transactions.</p>

<p>Keeping your connection limits in check should lead to a much healthier performing database and thus app.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Better database migrations in Postgres]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2017/09/10/better-postgres-migrations/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2017/09/10/better-postgres-migrations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As your database grows and scales there are some operations that you need to take more care of than you did when you were just starting. When working with your application in your dev environment you may not be fully aware of the cost of some operations until you run them against production. And at some point most of us have been guilty of it, running some migration that starts at 5 minutes, then 15 minutes in it&rsquo;s still running, and suddenly production traffic is impacted.</p>

<p>There are two operations that tend to happen quite frequently, each with some straightforward approaches to mitigate having any noticable amount of downtime. Let&rsquo;s look at each of the operations, how they work and then how you can approach them in a safer way. <!--more--></p>

<h3>Adding new columns</h3>

<p>Adding a new column is actually quite cheap in Postgres. When you do this it updates its underlying tracking of the columns that exist–which is almost instant. The part that becomes expensive is when you have some constraint against the column. A constraint could be a primary or foreign key, or some uniqueness constraint. Here Postgres has to scan through all the records in the table to ensure that it&rsquo;s not being violated. Adding some constraint such as <code>not null</code> does happen some, but is not the most common cause.</p>

<p>The most common reason for slowness of adding a new column is that most frameworks make it very simple for you to set a default value for the new column. It&rsquo;s one thing to do this for all new records, but when you do this when an existing table it means the database has to read all the records and re-write them with the new default value attached. This isn&rsquo;t so bad for a table with a few hundred records, but for a few hundred million run it then go get yourself coffee, or lunch, or a 5 course meal because you&rsquo;ll be waiting for a while.</p>

<p>In short, <code>not null</code> and setting a default value (on creation) of your new column will cause you pain. The solution is to not do those things. But, what if you want to have a default value and don&rsquo;t want to allow <code>nulls</code>. There&rsquo;s a few simple steps you can take, by essentially splitting your migration up from 1 step to 4 migrations:</p>

<ol>
<li>Add your new column <em>that allows nulls</em></li>
<li>Start writing your default value on all new records and updates</li>
<li>Gradually backfill the default value</li>
<li>Apply your constraint</li>
</ol>


<p>Yes, this is a little more work, but it doesn&rsquo;t impact production in nearly the same magnitude.</p>

<h3>Indexes</h3>

<p>Index creation like most DDL operations holds a lock while it&rsquo;s occurring, this means any new data has to wait for the index to be created and then the new writes flow through. Again when firsting creating the table or on a small table this time is not very noticable. On a large database though, you can again wait minutes to possibly even hours. <em>It&rsquo;s a bit ironic when you think about it that adding an index to speed things up can slow things down while it&rsquo;s happening.</em></p>

<p>Postgres of course has the answer for this with <code>CONCURRENT</code> index creation. What this does is gradually build up the index in the background. You can create your index concurrently with: <code>CREATE INDEX CONCURRENTLY</code>. As soon as the index is created and available as long as you did what you were hoping to Postgres will swap over to using it on queries.</p>

<h3>A tool to help</h3>

<p>It&rsquo;s a good practice to understand what is happening when you run a migration and its performance impact. That said you don&rsquo;t have to manage this all on your own. At least for Rails there&rsquo;s a tool to help enforce more of these as you&rsquo;re developing to catch it earlier. <a href="https://github.com/ankane/strong_migrations">Strong migrations</a> aims to catch many of these expensive operations for you to have your back, if you&rsquo;re on Rails consider giving it a look.</p>

<p>Have other tools or tips that can help with database migrations in Postgres? <a href="https://www.twitter.com/craigkerstiens">Drop me a note</a> and I&rsquo;ll work to add them to the list.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Postgres backups: Logical vs. Physical an overview]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2017/09/03/postgres-backups-physical-vs-logical/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2017/09/03/postgres-backups-physical-vs-logical</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s not a very disputed topic that you should backup your database, and further test your backups. What is a little less discussed, at least for Postgres, is the types of backups that exist. Within Postgres there are two forms of backups and understanding them is a useful foundation for anyone working with Postgres. The two backup types are</p>

<ol>
<li>Physical: which consist of the actual bytes on disk,</li>
<li>Logical: which is a more portable format.</li>
</ol>


<p>Let&rsquo;s dig into each a bit more so you can better assess which makes sense for you. <!--more--></p>

<h3>Logical backups</h3>

<p>Logical backups are the most well known type within Postgres. This is what you get when you run <code>pg_dump</code> against a database. There are a number of different formats you can get from <a href="http://postgresguide.com/utilities/backup-restore.html">logical backups</a> and Postgres does a good job of making it easy to compress and configure this backup how you see fit.</p>

<p>When a logical backup is run against a database it is not throttled, this introduces a noticable load on your database.</p>

<p>As it&rsquo;s reading the data from disk and generating (in layman terms) a bunch of SQL <code>INSERT</code> statements, it has to actually see the data. It&rsquo;s of note that older Postgres databases (read: prior to 9.3) there were no checksums against your database. Checksums are just one tool for you to help check against data corruption. Because a logical dump has to actually read and generate the data to insert it will discover any corruption that exists for you.</p>

<p>This portable format is also very useful to pull down copies from production to different environments. I.e. if you need a copy of production data down on your local laptop <code>pg_dump</code> is the way to do it. Logical backups are also database specific, but then allow you to dump only certain tables.</p>

<p>All in all logical backups bring some good features, but come at two cost:</p>

<ul>
<li>Load on your system</li>
<li>The backup contains data as of the time when it ran</li>
</ul>


<h3>Physical backups</h3>

<p>Physical backups are another option when it comes to backing up your database. As we mentioned earlier it is the physical bytes on disk. To understand physical backups we need to know a bit more under the covers about how Postgres works.</p>

<p>Postgres, under the covers, is essentially one giant append only log. When you insert data it gets written to the log known as the write-ahead log (commonly called WAL). When you update data a new record gets written to the WAL. When you delete data a new record gets written to the WAL. Nearly all changes in Postgres including to indexes and otherwise cause an update to the WAL.</p>

<p>With physical backups what you require to be able to create a restore of your database is two things:</p>

<ol>
<li>A <code>base backup</code>, which is a copy of the bytes on disk as of that point and time</li>
<li>Additional segments of the WAL to put the database in some consistent state.</li>
</ol>


<p>A physical backup only requires a small amount of WAL to restore the database to some valid state, <em>but</em> this also gives you some new flexibility. With a base backup plus WAL you can start to replay transactions up to a specific point in time. This is often how point-in-time recovery is performed within Postgres. If you accidentally drop a table, yes&hellip; it happens, you can:</p>

<ol>
<li>Find a base backup before you dropped the table</li>
<li>Restore that base backup</li>
<li>Replay wal segments up to roughly that time just before you dropped the table.</li>
</ol>


<p><em>If you&rsquo;re considering setting up physical backups, consider using a tool like <a href="https://www.citusdata.com/blog/2017/08/18/introducing-wal-g-faster-restores-for-postgres/">WAL-G</a> to help.</em></p>

<h3>Logical vs. Physical which to choose</h3>

<p>Both are useful and provide different benefits. At smaller scale, say under 100 GB of data logical backups via <code>pg_dump</code> are something you should absolutely be doing. Because backups happen quickly on smaller databases you may be able to get out without functionality like point-in-time recovery. At larger scale, as you approach 1 TB physical backups start to become your only option. Because of the load introduced by logical backups and the time lapse between capturing them they become less suitable for production.</p>

<p>Hopefully this primer helps provide a high level overview of the two primary types of backups that exist as options for Postgres. Of course there is much deeper you can go on each, but consider ensuring you have at least one of the two if not both in place. Oh and make sure to test them, an un-tested backup isn&rsquo;t a backup at all.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Postgres Open Silicon Valley line-up: First take]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2017/07/01/postgresopen-sv-line-up/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2017/07/01/postgresopen-sv-line-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This year Postgres open and PGConf SV have combined to great a bigger and better conference right in downtown San Francisco. <em>I&rsquo;m obviously biased as I&rsquo;m one of the co-chairs, and I know every conference organizer says picking the talks was hard, but I&rsquo;m especially excited for the line-up this year</em>. The hard part for me is going to be which talks do I miss out on because I&rsquo;m sitting in the other session that&rsquo;s ongoing. You can see the full list of <a href="https://postgresql.us/events/sessions/pgopen2017/">talk and tutorial sessions</a>, but I thought it&rsquo;d be fun to do a rundown of some of my favorites. <!--more--></p>

<h3><a href="https://postgresql.us/events/sessions/pgopen2017/session/399-how-postgres-could-index-itself/">How Postgres could index itself</a></h3>

<p><a href="https://postgresql.us/events/sessions/pgopen2017/session/399-how-postgres-could-index-itself/">Postgres indexing itself</a> has long been on my wishlist. <a href="https://www.twitter.com/akane">Andrew Kane</a> from Instacart, and creator of <a href="https://github.com/ankane/pghero/">PgHero</a> has bottled up many learnings into a new tool: <a href="https://medium.com/@ankane/introducing-dexter-the-automatic-indexer-for-postgres-5f8fa8b28f27">Dexter</a>. I suspect we&rsquo;ll get a look at all that went into this, how it works, and how you can leverage it to have a more automatically tuned database.</p>

<h3><a href="https://postgresql.us/events/sessions/pgopen2017/session/376-scaling-a-saas-application-beyond-a-single-postgres-with-citus/">Scaling a SaaS Application Beyond a Single Postgres with Citus</a></h3>

<p>Migration talks are all to common, from Postgres to MySQL from MySQL to Postgres, or from <a href="https://containership.engineering/dynamodb-to-postgres-why-and-how-aa891681af4d">Dynamo to Postgres</a>. But this one is a little different flavor from Postgres to sharded Postgres with <a href="https://www.citusdata.com">Citus</a>. Sharding into a distributed system of course brings new things to consider and think about, and <a href="https://postgresql.us/events/sessions/pgopen2017/session/376-scaling-a-saas-application-beyond-a-single-postgres-with-citus/">here you&rsquo;ll learn about them</a> from first hand experience so hopefully you can avoid mistakes yourself.</p>

<h3><a href="https://postgresql.us/events/sessions/pgopen2017/session/374-concurrency-deep-dive/">Concurrency Deep Dive</a></h3>

<p><a href="https://postgresql.us/events/sessions/pgopen2017/session/374-concurrency-deep-dive/">This one</a> looks to be a great under the hood look as well as likely very practical. It&rsquo;ll cover MVCC which is really at so much of the core of how Postgres works, but then bring it up to what it means for things like locks. Best of all, this one like so many others comes with lots of real world experience from Segment.</p>

<h3><a href="https://postgresql.us/events/sessions/pgopen2017/session/364-postgres-window-magic/">Postgres window magic</a></h3>

<p><img src="https://d3vv6lp55qjaqc.cloudfront.net/items/140p363n3b1N1X440Y0a/Image%202017-06-30%20at%2010.43.55%20AM.png?X-CloudApp-Visitor-Id=e4475d145dcf11ebcffabf840edcc11f&v=e35b6d4d" style="float:right; width:20%; margin-left:15px; " />
I love me some windows, though not always the easiest things to work with. They can let you easily do things like compute month over month growth between rows in a single query. Bruce whose always a great presenter <a href="https://postgresql.us/events/sessions/pgopen2017/session/364-postgres-window-magic/">walks us through them</a> and all the things they&rsquo;re capable of.</p>

<h3><a href="https://postgresql.us/events/sessions/pgopen2017/session/371-running-postgresql-instagram/">Running PostgreSQL @ Instagram</a></h3>

<p>Instagram is well known as one of the largest apps in the world. They optimized and changed their setup multiple times and probably scaled in about every way possible. <a href="https://postgresql.us/events/sessions/pgopen2017/session/371-running-postgresql-instagram/">Here we get to learn</a> about all the various things you need in running at a truly astonishing scale.</p>

<h3><a href="https://postgresql.us/events/sessions/pgopen2017/">Many many more</a></h3>

<p>Of course there&rsquo;s many more. Talks range from looks at new features, to how certain companies are using Postgres. We&rsquo;ve got companies like Instacart and Instagram as mentioned giving talks, to Postgres core committers. Whether you want to learn about the inner workings of Postgres (which often hurts my brain) to how you can simply speed up your app you should find something you like, as long as you like Postgres that is. Take a look at the <a href="https://postgresql.us/events/sessions/pgopen2017/">full list of sessions</a> and we hope to see you there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Working with time in Postgres]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2017/06/08/working-with-time-in-postgres/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.craigkerstiens.com/2017/06/08/working-with-time-in-postgres</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A massive amount of reporting queries, whether really intensive data analysis, or just basic insights into your business involving looking at data over a certain time period. Postgres has really rich support for dealing with time out of the box, something that&rsquo;s often very underweighted when dealing with a database. Sure, if you have a time-series database it&rsquo;s implied, but even then how flexible and friendly is it from a query perspective? With Postgres there&rsquo;s a lot of key items available to you, let&rsquo;s dig in at the things that make your life easier when querying. <!--more--></p>

<h3>Date math</h3>

<p>The most common thing I find myself doing is looking at users that have done something within some specific time window. If I&rsquo;m executing this all from my app I can easily inject specific dates, but Postgres makes this really easy for you. Within Postgres you have a type called an interval that is some window of time. And fortunately Postgres takes care of the heavy lifting of how might something translate to or from hours/seconds/milliseconds/etc. Here&rsquo;s just a few examples of things you could do with interals:</p>

<ul>
<li>&lsquo;1 day&rsquo;::interval</li>
<li>&lsquo;5 days&rsquo;::interval</li>
<li>&lsquo;1 week&rsquo;::interval</li>
<li>&lsquo;30 days&rsquo;::interval</li>
<li>&lsquo;1 month&rsquo;::interval</li>
</ul>


<p><em>A note that if you&rsquo;re looking to remove something like a full month, you actually want to use 1 month instead of trying to calculate yourself.</em></p>

<p>With a given interval you can easily shift some window of time, such as finding all users that have signed up for your service within the past week:</p>

<p><code>sql
SELECT *
FROM users
WHERE created_at &gt;= now() - '1 week'::interval
</code></p>

<h3>Date functions</h3>

<p>Date math makes it pretty easy for you to go and find some specific set of data that applies, but what do you do when you want a broader report around time? There&rsquo;s a few options here. One is to leverage the built-in Postgres functions that help you work with dates and times. <code>date_trunc</code> is one of the most used ones that will truncate a date down to some interval level. Here you can use the same general values as the above, but simply pass in the type of interval it will be. So if we wanted to find the count of users that signed up per week:</p>

<p>```
SELECT date_trunc(&lsquo;week&rsquo;, created_at),</p>

<pre><code>   count(*)
</code></pre>

<p>FROM users
GROUP BY 1
ORDER BY 1 DESC;
```</p>

<p>This gives us a nice roll-up of how many users signed up each week. What&rsquo;s missing here though is if you have a week that has no users. In that case because no users signed up there is no count of 0, it just simply doesn&rsquo;t exist. If you did want something like this you could generate some range of time and then do a cross join with it against users to see which week they fell into. To do this first you&rsquo;d generate a series of dates:</p>

<p><code>sql
SELECT generate_series('2017-01-01'::date, now()::date, '1 week'::interval) weeks
</code></p>

<p>Then we&rsquo;re going to join this against the actual users table and check that the <code>created_at</code> falls within the right range.</p>

<p>```
with weeks as (
  select week
  from generate_series(&lsquo;2017-01-01&rsquo;::date, now()::date, &lsquo;1 week&rsquo;::interval) week
)</p>

<p>SELECT weeks.week,</p>

<pre><code>   count(*)
</code></pre>

<p>FROM weeks,</p>

<pre><code> users
</code></pre>

<p>WHERE users.created_at > weeks.week
  AND users.created_at &lt;= (weeks.week &ndash; &lsquo;1 week&rsquo;::interval)
GROUP BY 1
ORDER BY 1 DESC;
```</p>

<h3>Timestamp vs. Timestamptz</h3>

<p>What about storing the times themselves? Postgres has two types of timestamps. It has a generic timestamp and one with timezone embedded in it. In most cases you should generally opt for timestamptz. Why not timestamp? What happens if you move a server, or your server somehow swaps its configuration. Or perhaps more practically what about daylight savings time? In general you might think that you can simply just put in the time as you see it, but when different countries around the world observe things like daylight savings time differently it introduces complexities into your application.</p>

<p>With timestamptz it&rsquo;ll be aware of the extra parts of your timezone as it comes in. Then when you query from one timezone that accounts for daylights savings you&rsquo;re all covered. There&rsquo;s a <a href="http://phili.pe/posts/timestamps-and-time-zones-in-postgresql/">number of articles</a> that cover a bit more in depth on the logic between timestamp and timestamp with timezone, so if you&rsquo;re curious I encourage you to check them out, but by default you mostly just need to use timestamptz.</p>

<h3>More</h3>

<p>There&rsquo;s a number of other functions and capabilities when it comes to dealing with time in Postrges. You can <code>extract</code> various parts of a timesetamp or interval such as hour of the day or the month. You can grab the day of the week with <code>dow</code>. And one of my favorites which is when we celebrate happy hour at Citus, there&rsquo;s a literal for UTC 00:00:00 00:00:00 which is <a href="https://www.postgresql.org/message-id/20050124200645.GA6126%40winnie.fuhr.org"><code>allballs()</code></a>. If you need to work with dates and times in Postgres I encourage you to check out the <a href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/static/functions-datetime.html">docs</a> before you try to re-write something of your own, chances are what you need may already be there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
